<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The three last sermons preached by the late Reverend Mr. Timothy Cruso, who dyed Novem. 26, 1697 to which is added his sermon on the 5th Nov. 1697.</title>
            <author>Cruso, Timothy, 1656?-1697.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1698</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 125 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 45 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A35325</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C7444</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R31349</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11927298</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11927298</idno>
            <idno type="VID">51055</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A35325)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 51055)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1001:14)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The three last sermons preached by the late Reverend Mr. Timothy Cruso, who dyed Novem. 26, 1697 to which is added his sermon on the 5th Nov. 1697.</title>
                  <author>Cruso, Timothy, 1656?-1697.</author>
                  <author>Fuller, Francis, 1637?-1701.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 78 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by S. Bridge for Tho. Parkhurst ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1698.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"To the reader" signed: F. Fuller.</note>
                  <note>Errata on p. [7].</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the University of Illinois (Urbana-Champaign Campus). Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
               <term>Dissenters, Religious --  England.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:51055:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:51055:1"/>
            <p>THE Three Laſt Sermons, PREACHED By the Late Reverend Mr. <hi>Timothy Cruſo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Who Dyed, <hi>Novem.</hi> 26. 1697.</p>
            <p>To which is added His SERMON On the <hi>5th. Nov.</hi> 1697.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed by <hi>S. Bridge,</hi> for <hi>Tho. Park-hurſt</hi> at the <hi>Bible</hi> and <hi>Three Crowns</hi> in <hi>Cheapſide</hi> near <hi>Mercers-Chapel,</hi> 1698.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:51055:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:51055:2"/>
            <head>TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>THE Reverend Author of theſe Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, was well known for his Emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nency in Miniſterial Abilities, and his great Faithfulneſs and Diligence in the Exerciſe of them, to his Honour from whom he had receiv'd them, and to whom they were wholy Due.</p>
            <p>He had a good <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding in the Viſions of God, and found out (as the Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er did) acceptable Words to explain them, ſuch as did at once, both Pleaſe,<note place="margin">Eccleſ. 12.10.</note> and Profit. By his skilfulneſs in thoſe Viſions, he was as Eyes to the Blind, and by his Dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence in the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe of it, he conſum'd himſelf (like a Taper) by giving Light to others, which makes the Loſs the greater, and the Repair the more difficult.</p>
            <p>The Argument he makes uſe of to perſwade backſliding Sinners to return to God, is ground<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed on the Divine Precept, and the Divine Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe;
<pb facs="tcp:51055:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>on the Precept, as the Ground of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, and on the Promiſe, as the Ground of Confidence; on that, as their Warrant, and on this, as their Encouragement to it.</p>
            <p>Sin has indeed made a Separation between God and Sinners as to his Grace and Favour, though not as to his Eſſence and Power: But a New and Living Way by Chriſt (who united God to Man in Favour, by Uniting God to Man in Perſon) is opened, wherein, they who are at a great Diſtance from God, and deſerve to be ſet at an irrecoverable Diſtance from him, may have free Acceſs to him. The Command ſhows they muſt com, and the Promiſe, that with Hope they may, that makes it neceſſary to be done, and this Beneficial, if it is.</p>
            <p>The ſwiftneſs of the Compaſſionate Fathers Motion towards the returning Prodigal Son, (who <hi>ran</hi> while he did but <hi>come</hi>) and the great Entertainment he made for him when come, ſhew, how willing the Father was, that he ſhould come, and how Welcome the Son was when he did come, ſtands upon Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord to expreſs that great Compaſſion in God to Sinners (who more willingly calls them than they either are, or can) be to come at his call; and that delicate Proviſion, the beſt, and ſweetest (a Feast of Fat Things, the ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est Part of Meat, and of Marrow, the ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est Part of Fat) and thoſe ſtrong and pure Conſolations (Wine on the Lees well refin'd, one noting Strength, and the other Purity) that he Feeds them with in the Way in his Banqueting-houſe (the Houſe of Pleaſure and
<pb facs="tcp:51055:3"/>Feaſting) the foretasts of that better Chear reſerv'd for them in the Manſion-houſe, thoſe Everlaſting Conſolations, that are ever the ſame, always ſatiating without Loathing, and ever Renewing without Finiſhing.</p>
            <p>This Good-Will of God to Sinners on his Part might allure them to come, but the Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity on their Part to come, ſhould Compel them to it; for, their is no <hi>Medium</hi> betwixt Salvation and Damnation, nor any Way to obtain the one, or eſcape the other, but by Coming.</p>
            <p>The Philoſopher tells us,<note place="margin">Ar. Rh. <hi>l. 1. c. 9.</hi>
               </note> that there is no Counſel about things of Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity, they admit no Debate, Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſibility is a Hinderance to Reaſon, Difficulty is a Hinderance to Sloth, but Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity Quickens to Action; and would they but ſet the Neceſſity against the Difficulty, they would either find no Difficulty, or make it none, by overcoming it, eſpecially in a Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of that Moment, where a Delay makes the Caſe dangerous, and a total Neglect makes it deſperate.</p>
            <p>You have Gods Call to come, let him have your Anſwer, that you will come; that you are coming (behold we come) with your Call to him to draw you that you may come, (for there is no Coming to him, but by Strength from him;) and with full purpoſe of Heart cleave to him when come; for, without it, you would not be receiv'd though you did come, for you come before you are call'd, and ſhall be ſent away as you come.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:51055:4"/>
            <p>Now that what is here Publiſhed may be Read and Bleſs'd to an effectual prevailing with Sinners, to turn from Sin to God; ſo from Sin, as never more to turn to it, and ſo to God, as never willingly to turn away from him; is the ſincere Deſire</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Of your Friend and Servant in our Lord.</hi> F. Fuller.</signed>
               <dateline>
                  <date>April, <hi>5th. 1698.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:51055:4"/>
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>PAge 3. Line 14. for <hi>yet</hi> read <hi>that,</hi> p. 8. l. 1. after <hi>for</hi> r. <hi>firſt of all,</hi> p. 13. l. 8. r. <hi>it is</hi> before <hi>the,</hi> p. 14. l. 23. r. <hi>for</hi> before <hi>what,</hi> p. 15. l. 15. r. <hi>through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out,</hi> p. 37. l. 26. for <hi>how</hi> r. <hi>what,</hi> p. 45. l. 9. for <hi>the</hi> r. <hi>who,</hi> p. 49. l. 6. after <hi>not</hi> r. <hi>that,</hi> p. 70. l. 19. r. <hi>they.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:51055:5"/>
            <head>Theſe Books lately Printed for <hi>Tho. Parkhurſt.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>DIſcourſes upon the Rich Man and <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zarus.</hi> By Mr. <hi>Tim. Cruſo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There is now Publiſhed, thoſe two ſcarce and excellent Books the Fountain of Life opened, in Forty Two Sermons. And a Treatiſe of the Soul of Man, in 4to. Both by the Late Reverend and Learned Mr. <hi>John Flavel</hi> Miniſter of the Goſpel at <hi>Dart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Howes</hi> Sermon on the Day of Thankſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giving.</p>
            <p>— His Sermon for Reformation of Manners.</p>
            <p>— His Sermon at the Funeral of Mr. <hi>Rich. Adams,</hi> M. A.</p>
            <p>The great Duty and comfortable Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, keeping our ſelves from our Ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity, open'd and applied. By <hi>John Whit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lock</hi> Miniſter of the Goſpel in <hi>Notting<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Perſwaſive to full Communion with the Churches of Chriſt in all Goſpel-Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances and Priviledges. By the Late Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verend Mr. <hi>George Day</hi> Miniſter of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel in <hi>London-ſtreet</hi> in <hi>Ratcliff.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A ſhort Hiſtory of the Late War be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween King <hi>William,</hi> the <hi>Confederates</hi> and the <hi>French</hi> King.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermons">
            <div n="1" type="sermon">
               <pb n="1" facs="tcp:51055:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>SERMON I.</hi> Of Converſion to God.</head>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>JER. III. 22. latter part.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                     <p>Behold we come unto Thee! For Thon art the Lord our God.</p>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>THERE are ſeveral earneſt Exhortations by the Prophet in this Chapter, to ſollicite and perſuade the unfeigned Converſion of a ſinful People to God. As <hi>ver.</hi> 1. again, <hi>ver.</hi> 7. then <hi>ver.</hi> 12. and laſtly in this <hi>ver.</hi> 22. which repreſents a kind of Dialogue be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween God and the People of the <hi>Jews;</hi> his Speech to them in the former Part of the Verſe, and their Reply to him in the latter Part of it; What he ſays, is full of Kindneſs and Affection; What they ſay, is expreſſive of their Duty and Submiſſion.</p>
               <p n="1">1. What <hi>God</hi> ſays, This contains a Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept and a Promiſe. A Precept, <hi>Return you
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:51055:6"/>backſliding Children:</hi> A Promiſe, <hi>And I will heal your Backſliding.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. What the <hi>People</hi> ſay; both with Refe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence to the Act it ſelf, <hi>Behold we come un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Thee;</hi> and the Reaſon of it, <hi>For thou art the Lord our God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Whether the <hi>Jews</hi> were ever really pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailed with to do after this Manner, by the Miniſtry of the Prophet, is very doubtful; or whether this were a Prophecy concerning the Time to come; (though it be ſpoken in the Time preſent here, and in the Time paſt, <hi>ver.</hi> 21. <hi>A Voice was heard,</hi> &amp;c.) is alſo queſtionable: But this is certain, that the Prophet ſpeaking in the Name of this People, in the cloſe of the Verſe, as he had done in the Name of God, in the beginning of it, ſets down what was proper and meet to be ſaid: As when <hi>Iſrael</hi> was admoniſh'd, <hi>To return to the Lord their God,</hi> Hoſ. 14.1. Words were put into their Mouths, fit to take with them at their return, <hi>ver.</hi> 2. So here, the Command being given for their Return, here is a plain Inſtruction what they ſhould Anſwer, which would be as a Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony againſt them, if they refuſed to do it.</p>
               <p>Obſ. <hi>'Tis a bleſſed Thing, when Sinners are effectually inclined to come to God in Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to his Precept; and upon the En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragement of his Promiſe.</hi> Here,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:51055:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <list>
                     <item>1. Shew what it is for Sinners to come to God?</item>
                     <item>2. How they ſhould do it in Obedience to the Precept, and upon the Encouragement of the Promiſe.</item>
                     <item>3. Wherein lies the Bleſſedneſs of this.</item>
                     <item>4. The Uſe.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p n="1">I. <hi>What is it for Sinners to come to God?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> It does not imply any change of natural Place, ſecular Employment, or Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil Relation, but of ſpiritual State.</p>
               <p>There are three Things eſpecially in it.</p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>A Relinquiſhing of every Thing that is contrary to God, and yet keeps us at a diſtanc from him.</hi> To come to God, and bring our Luſts along with us, and deſign the retain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of them, is utterly inconſiſtent; 'tis an aggravated Abomination, as if we had a mind to unite <hi>God</hi> and <hi>Belial,</hi> or to bring about an Agreement between Heaven and Hell, which is as impoſſible as to travel <hi>Eaſt</hi> and <hi>Weſt</hi> at the ſame Time. Whenever the Spirit Works an Inclination in any Soul to return to God, there is alſo wrought a ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere Deſire of Separation from every Sin. There's nothing more plain and evident, through the Scripture than this is, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 55.7. <hi>Let the Wicked forſake his Way, and the unrighteous Man his Thoughts, and let him re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn unto the Lord,</hi> &amp;c. All returning ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes and includes an abandoning of that
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:51055:7"/>which is offenſive and diſpleaſing to him, to whom we return; <hi>Ezek.</hi> 18.31. <hi>Caſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way from you all your Tranſgreſſions, whereby you have tranſgreſſed,</hi> &amp;c. If a Rebel intend to ſubmit to his Soveraign Prince, he will not come with the Weapons of his Rebelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on into his Princes Preſence, but leave them behind him. That Grace which turns the Heart towards God, does always ſet the Heart againſt all fleſhly and worldly Luſts: It no ſooner ſeeks to have to do with <hi>him,</hi> but 'tis made truly willing to have no more to do with <hi>them.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>A making uſe of Chriſt as the Way to God.</hi> Chriſt is ſo, and muſt be uſed as ſuch, by every returning Sinner that would proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per in his Way. God is inacceſſible with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a Mediator; He opens the Paſſage be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt God and us, which Sin and Wrath had ſhut up; he enables us to come, though lamed by the Fall, ſets us on our Feet and holds up our goings. We muſt look to <hi>Christ</hi> as the giver of <hi>Repentance,</hi> as well as of <hi>Forgiveneſs,</hi> Acts 5.31.</p>
               <p>Two Things ought to be ſeriouſly conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered and impreſt upon our Minds in this Caſe.</p>
               <p n="1">1. That there would have been no place for <hi>Repentance,</hi> if <hi>Chriſt</hi> had not interpoſed with his Blood. Repentance would have ſignified nothing, if he had not purchaſed Forgiveneſs. The Penitent would have been as far off from Pardon, as the moſt Impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitent,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:51055:7"/>if that Pardon had not been meri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toriouſly obtained by the Death of Chriſt.</p>
               <p n="2">2. There never would have been any Principle or Exerciſe of Repentance, if Chriſt did not produce it by his Spirit. The natural hardneſs of every Heart ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludes the leaſt Diſpoſitions to ſound and ſaving Repentance, till he hath ſoftned and ſubdued it: Therefore <hi>Christ</hi> muſt be eyed as making us what God requires us to be, for our Repentance is not only accepted on the account of his <hi>Sufferings,</hi> but acted by vertue of his <hi>Grace.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>A giving up of our ſelves to God, and reſting in him as our End.</hi> The Scope of a Sinners coming to God, is not anſwered, without entire and abſolute Reſignation. When we come to God it is in order to our being diſpoſed and governed by him, as he thinks fit; not doing our own Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure but being Subject to his. Except <hi>we yield our ſelves to God,</hi> Rom. 6.13. we do not really and heartily Return to him; for by our return we pretend to acknowledge the <hi>right</hi> which he hath in us, and the <hi>wrong</hi> which we have done to him, by living ſo long without him, and in Enmity againſt him. If the Sinner do not reſolve to make the Will of God the ſtanding rule of his fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture Practice, he does but affront God and deceive himſelf with a mock Repentance. Whoſoever hath been in Dominion hereto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, it muſt be only allowed to God for
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:51055:8"/>Time to come, and to him unreſervedly. And whereſoever we have rambled and ſtrayed in the vain purſuit of Happineſs and Satisfaction, like thoſe that have <hi>for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten their reſting Place,</hi> Jer. 50.6. We are to make a final ſtop at our coming to God, and look no further. Here we are to ſit down and fix, as having found that Good which is incomparably the beſt, and moſt worthy to be choſen: For he that can ever think of removing from God, with hopes of mending his Condition, is a wretched Hypocrite, and hath not returned in good Earneſt.</p>
               <p n="2">II. <hi>How ſhould Sinners come to God,</hi> in <hi>O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience</hi> to the <hi>Precept,</hi> and upon the <hi>Encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement</hi> of the <hi>Promiſe?</hi> For this penitent Profeſſion here in the Text is brought in, as the iſſue and reſult of both.</p>
               <p n="1">1. How muſt they come in <hi>Obedience</hi> to the <hi>Precept?</hi> God calls to them to return; In what manner are they to do it, with re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect to his Call?</p>
               <p n="1">I Anſwer in two Things.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Sinners are to come to God <hi>humbly;</hi> and that in Conſideration of the Command of God, upon two Accounts.</p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>All Acts of Obedience to God are to be performed with Humbleneſs of Mind.</hi> 'Tis be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coming a Creature as being under Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, though innocent and ſinleſs. Pride of
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:51055:8"/>Heart is enough to corrupt the beſt ſervice of the holieſt Angel in Heaven. Inordinate lifting up, was the fatal caſting down and Condemnation of the Devil. It is an Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour to a Creature to receive any Commands from its Maker, and obey them; but this Honour is to be worn with Humility; we are in our beſt Eſtate ſo much below God, that we are unworthy of being employed or commanded by him; and ſo long as <hi>Adam</hi> retain'd his Integrity, he was ſenſible of this.</p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>Returning to God after former Acts of Diſobedience, requires ſpecial Humiliation.</hi> So it follows here, <hi>ver.</hi> 25. <hi>We lye down in our ſhame, and our Confuſion covereth us, for we have ſinned againſt the Lord our God, and have not obeyed his Voice.</hi> A ſincere Convert muſt needs be ſtruck with ſhame, under a Senſe of his wicked Departings. We can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not reflect, how we have tranſgreſt without Cauſe, and run away from God without Provocation, but that we muſt ſee abundance of Reaſon for the deepeſt Self-abaſement. We cannot ſay, that we ever found any Ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity in God, but we have a great deal to charge upon our ſelves; all the Commands which we have broken have been juſt, and therefore an humbling Conviction of our Guilt is neceſſary.</p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>We are to come to God readily.</hi> Inſtant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly with all the haſte and ſpeed we can, or elſe the Precept does not ſway us in our
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:51055:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>coming as it ought to do; for we are born under a Law to God, his Commands oblige us aſſoon as we have a Being. We can name no Time wherein 'tis not the Duty of the Sinner to return to God, therefore the leaſt delay is increaſed Diſobedience. And diſobedience to the <hi>preſent Call</hi> is no more excuſable then diſobedience to the <hi>next,</hi> if you ſhould ever have another. We are as much bound to come <hi>now,</hi> as at any other ſeaſon. The Authority of God enjoyning it, ſhould be Argument enough with us, and that Argument we have now, conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently, if we will hear his Voice; defer not hearing of that till <hi>to Morrow,</hi> which ſhould be heard <hi>to Day.</hi> When God is ſo kind to admit your Return, there is no Reaſon that he ſhould wait for it.</p>
               <p n="2">2. We are further off from Coming to God, the longer we go on in Sin: The Command will have ſo much the leſs Force upon us, the more dilatory we are in our Obedience to it. If every Sinner in the World, would ingenuouſly declare his own Experience, he could not deny the Truth of this; his own Conſcience tells him that he ſinds it ſo to be. Every Days Sins put him at a greater diſtance from God, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get a greater Backwardneſs and Averſion to return. He that tarries till <hi>hereafter,</hi> will be more unwillig <hi>then,</hi> than he is <hi>now.</hi> Who can tell but that your Preſumption now, may be then changed into Deſpair, and the
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:51055:9"/>ſame Tempter that now ſuggeſts that 'tis <hi>too ſoon,</hi> may then tell you that it is <hi>too late?</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. How muſt they come upon the <hi>Encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement</hi> of the <hi>Promiſe?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>God ſays, he will heal the Sinners Back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlidings, whatſoever, or how many ſoever they have been. In what Manner ſhould they come with Relation to this,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> In two Things: With <hi>Faith</hi> and <hi>Joy.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. Sinners are to come to God <hi>Believing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,</hi> with regard to the <hi>Promiſe:</hi> For theſe two Reaſons.</p>
               <p n="1">1. If <hi>Faith</hi> be not the Spring of all our Motions towards God, they cannot be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable to him. You cannot provoke God more, then by making him a Lyar, which is the Language and Tendency of Unbelief, 1 <hi>John</hi> 5.10. To come to him with diſtruſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Apprehenſions of him, is to caſt as foul a Reproach upon him as is poſſible to be raked out of the bottomleſs Pit. He that comes to God muſt Believe or he cannot be welcome; he muſt believe <hi>in God</hi> as more ready to Forgive, than he is to Repent in his beſt and moſt melting frame; he muſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve <hi>in Christ</hi> as one who has more Power to ſave, than all his Sin hath to deſtroy.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The Promiſe does encourage ſuch a Faith, as much as we need or can deſire.
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:51055:10"/>Beſides his gracious Entreaties, affectionate Offers, importunate Pleadings, you have his poſitive Aſſurances that he will receive you, if you return, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.17. He cannot re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject you without denying of himſelf; his Word belongs to every one alike that laies hold of it, and it will as certainly be verifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and fulfilled to <hi>you,</hi> as ever it was to <hi>any.</hi> You may as well Queſtion, whether ever God embraced one Sinner that came to him as doubt of your own Reception, upon your compliance with his Call. Unleſs you think that he hath excluded <hi>all,</hi> why ſhould you ſuſpect that he will caſt out <hi>you?</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. Sinners muſt come <hi>Joyfully</hi> to God. The Promiſe is ground of rejoycing, as well as of Hope and Truſt; and God never de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned, that our Sorrow for Sin ſhould be ſo extream, as to ſtifle or drown the <hi>Joy</hi> of Converſion. This will appear, if we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider.</p>
               <p n="1">1. That <hi>God who makes the Promiſe, rejoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces in the Performance.</hi> The Scripture does not barely ſay, that he will ſave, but that <hi>he will rejoyce over thee with Joy,</hi> Zeph. 3.17. Even <hi>over thee,</hi> that has ſinfully grieved his Spirit ſo many thouſand Times over. A loſt Sheep is a pleaſant Load to a Man that hath found it, and laies it on his Shoulders, he does it <hi>rejoycing,</hi> Luke 15.15. So 'tis pleaſant Work to God to fetch home a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellious Sinner, and when returned to lay him in his Boſom. If his <hi>Patience</hi> could bear
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:51055:10"/>ſo long with thy Sins, gueſs how delightful the Exerciſe of his <hi>Mercy</hi> muſt be, upon thy Repentance. And ſhould not that which is <hi>his Joy,</hi> be much more <hi>Ours?</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>We who have the Benefit of the Promiſe, muſt needs be ſtill doubtful of it, if we do not Rejoyce in it.</hi> If we ſearch to the bottom in this Caſe, we ſhall find that 'tis <hi>Infidelity</hi> which cramps our <hi>Joy;</hi> this makes the Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner come drooping and trembling to God, when he ſhould come (as that Lame man entred with the Apoſtles into the Temple, after they had healed him. <hi>Acts</hi> 3.8.) <hi>leap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and praiſing,</hi> triumphing and glorying in the Lord. How can we think of being re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived by God, after ſo long and hainous a Revolt, but that it muſt raviſh our Hearts, if we believed it to be true? If we had Faith ſuitable to the faithfulneſs of God, it would tranſport the Soul into an Extaſie, that we who have lifted up our Heels ſo oft againſt God, ſhould be taken into his Arms.</p>
               <p n="3">III. Wherein lies <hi>the Bleſſedneſs of this?</hi> When Sinners are thus effectually inclined to come to God; When the Precept and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe work ſo upon them, as to influence their actual Return.</p>
               <p n="1">1. When a Sinner comes back to God, he is brought out of a moſt miſerable Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſs Condition, wherein if he had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mained he muſt have periſhed. Inſtead of
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:51055:11"/>faring better or ſo well any where elſe, as with God, no Sinner can ſtay where he is, remote from God, without inevitable De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction. If he ſits ſtill he muſt dye; there's no way of eſcape. How ſecure and proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous ſoever Men be for the preſent, yet they are indeed loſt and undone, if they do not return to <hi>God;</hi> for all the World cannot defend them againſt God, nor make them Happy in the want of him.</p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>They cannot defend them againſt God.</hi> Who or what can deliver out of his Hand? If his Wrath be kindled who can quench it? He in his Anger overturns the Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains, as firm as they are, with more eaſe than we can move a Feather, <hi>Job</hi> 9.5. What Created Power is great enough to grapple with Omnipotence? Whither can we ſly for help, when Almighty Revenge is following of us?</p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>They cannot make Happy in the want of God.</hi> The whole World would be a ſorry Recompence and a poor Supply, for any one Man that were to live without God in it. The thirſty Soul cannot take its fill at ſuch broken Ciſterns, but its Thirſt will conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue, unleſs it have recourſe to the Fountain. Set <hi>God</hi> aſide, and every thing elſe is as no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, and will leave Men unſatisfied.</p>
               <p n="2">2. When a Sinner comes to God, <hi>Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> comes to him. As Chriſt ſaid to <hi>Zac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheus,</hi> Luke. 19.9. <hi>This Day is Salvation come to this Houſe,</hi> &amp;c. Sound Converſion
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:51055:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>and certain Salvation are inſeparable; they never were, nor ever can be divided. He that hath heartily renounced his Sin, and is returned to God, is from that Time for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward an apparent Heir of Salvation; and may be numbred with the ſaved of the Lord. <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nto us which are ſaved,</hi> &amp;c. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.18. <hi>Salvation</hi> is either <hi>Final,</hi> or <hi>Initial;</hi> the ſame Salvation, only diſtinguiſht as to order of Time, wherein 'tis gradnally wrought and carried on: Final Salvation is the Priviledge of the glorified Saint, Initial Salvation is the Portion of the new-born Convert, both run into one; he that is ſaved <hi>Initially</hi> ſhall be ſaved <hi>Finally;</hi> Salvation truly begun, will be Salvation fully compleated. Every Babe in Chriſt hath the real <hi>firſt Fruits of the Spirit,</hi> Rom. 8.2. And he that hath thoſe firſt Fruits cannot fail of the Harveſt of Glory. Salvation takes in all Spiritual Bleſſings at once, and Eternal Bleſſings are chained to them. Every Child of God aſſoon as he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turns to his Duty, hath a Title given him to all the Riches of his Fathers Houſe; he may look up to Heaven and ſay, I have a large Inheritance there, which Earth and Hell cannot deprive me of.</p>
               <p n="3">3. When a Sinner comes home to God, all his <hi>fellow Creatures</hi> ſhall be ſome way or other ſerviceable to him; either willingly and gladly, or by conſtraint and over-ruling Neceſſity. The whole Creation is on Gods ſide, and will take Part with him againſt his
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:51055:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>Adverſaries; ſo that no Creature can be at Peace with us, till we are reconciled to him; but after that, they all immediately turn to be our Friends; or at the leaſt, all the En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity which we meet with, ſhall be turned to our Advantage. Either <hi>nothing ſhall hurt us,</hi> as Chriſt told his Diſciples; <hi>Luke</hi> 10.19. or the hurt which we receive ſhall be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quited with a far greater and more excellent Good. Angels above us will encamp round about us, be miniſtring to us, and do all the friendly Offices for us, that we can wiſh to have done. The beſt of Men who are Creatures of the ſame order and rank with us, are all for our uſe ſo far as we ſhall need them; and as for Devils and the worſt of Men, we ſhall have Gods Protection from their Malice, or his Influence to ſanctifie us by it.</p>
               <p n="4">4. When a Sinner is come to God, he may viſit God by <hi>Prayer</hi> in all his Neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and be ſure of ſufficient Relief. He may go afterwards to the Throne of Grace, what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever he lacks freely and boldly, and ſhall ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver be treated as a Stranger, nor ſent away empty. To have Liberty of doing this in any peculiar extraordinary Strait, would be a mighty Favour; but what a Priviledge muſt it be to do it always, every Day, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on every occaſion, and to know that God will not be wearied, but rather pleaſed and delighted with our continual coming. It is a proud miſtake for any Creature to think
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:51055:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>that they can live of themſelves, though it was that which the <hi>Jews</hi> ſtand arraigned for; <hi>Jer.</hi> 2.31. <hi>Wherefore ſay my People, we are Lords, we will come no more to Thee?</hi> They might better have ſaid, we are <hi>Beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gars,</hi> and cannot ſubſiſt without coming to thee. This is indeed our Caſe, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore 'tis well for us, that we are not debar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red from Coming; yea we are invited to come as often as we will, and the oftner we come, the better we ſucceed; this is the Happineſs of a Sinner after his Converſion, but not before it.</p>
               <p n="5">5. A Sinner that is come to God, may ſweetly walk and <hi>Converſe with God,</hi> through the reſidue of his Life; and the benefit and ſweetneſs of ſuch Communion is not to be imagined by thoſe that have it not, they that are far from God can be no Judges of the Bleſſedneſs of thoſe that are near unto him. The Preſence of God is a glorious Priviledge which can never be valued high enough, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven by them that do poſſeſs it; none can tell what a bleſſed Thing it is, to be able to ſay, as the Pſalmiſt does, <hi>I am continually with Thee,</hi> Pſalm 73.23. When I lye down, when I riſe up, when I go out, when I come in, when Providence ſmiles upon me, and when it frowns, when I enjoy the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Mercies that are moſt deſirable, when I ſuffer the outward Afflictions that are moſt uneaſie; <hi>I am ſtill with God.</hi> So long as my Sin is put away, nothing now can ſeparate
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:51055:13"/>me from him; on the other Hand, while Sin remains, there can be no ſuch Fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip; in whatſoever State I am, 'tis moſt certain, that I am <hi>abſent from God,</hi> a meer Out-caſe, a Fugitive, a Vagabond, like <hi>Cain</hi> excluded from all amicable Correſpondence with him.</p>
               <p n="6">6. A Sinner that is come to God, may go to him with Comfort and Conſidence at <hi>Death,</hi> whether ſooner or later, <hi>when a few Years</hi> (it may be Days or Minutes) <hi>are come, then I ſhall go the Way whence I ſhall not return,</hi> Job 16.22. We muſt in a little while go to God, <hi>as a Judge,</hi> whether we will or not, and immediately thereupon our Everlaſting State will be unalterably ſixt, and what is not done before is impoſſible to be done after it. Now none are prepared to go to God <hi>as a Judge,</hi> but what are firſt returned to him as a <hi>Father;</hi> and what an unſpeakable Mercy is it to be ſo prepared? With how much Peace and Quietneſs may a Man paſs the Time of his Sojourning here, that hath no Reaſon to be afraid of departing hence? The <hi>Terror</hi> of <hi>Dying</hi> makes it a <hi>Bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage</hi> to <hi>Live;</hi> but when once God hath re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived a Sinner through Chriſt, the Grounds of thoſe Fears are taken away; ſuch a one may at any Time leave the World, and go forth out of the Body, with a chearful un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daunted Spirit in the ſame Hope that the Pſalmiſt had, <hi>For God ſhall receive me,</hi> Pſalm 49.15.</p>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:51055:13"/>
               <p n="4">IV. Uſe.</p>
               <p n="1">1. This ſhews that they who will not come <hi>to God</hi> are not come <hi>to themſelves.</hi> So ſoon as the Prodigal came to himſelf, he preſently Thought of returning to his Father, <hi>Luke</hi> 15.17. When <hi>Nebuchadnez<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zar</hi>'s Underſtanding returned to him, he Bleſſed the moſt High, and Praiſed and Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured him that liveth for ever, <hi>Dan.</hi> 4.34. He had lived like a <hi>Bruit</hi> before, and ſo do all that are alienated from God, and turn their backs upon him. religion makes <hi>us</hi> mad in their Eſteem, but the want of it makes <hi>them</hi> truly ſo. They think that we who urge their Converſion are <hi>beſides our ſelves,</hi> but 'tis a Sign that they are <hi>ſo indeed,</hi> becauſe they will not hearken.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Miniſters will have a dreadful and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſing Account to give of thoſe, whom they leave unperſwaded. Our Time is ſhort and the Hour is coming, when we muſt leave this Work of Beſeeching, and Preſſing, and Arguing with you, and go to him that ſent us, with a faithful account of the Iſſue of our Meſſage. 'Tis againſt our Minds, againſt our Prayers, againſt the whole Purpoſe of our Miniſtry, to accuſe any of you to the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: But we muſt do it, if you will not prevent it by hearing and obeying. It will be a Melancholy thing and Matter of Grief, <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.7. For one that hath laboured in this Goſpel to ſtand forth at the great Day,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:51055:14"/>and produce no Fruits; Here we are, but they that were bidden and invited in thy Name by us refuſed to come. We warn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, we begg'd, we did what we could, but they would not yield, and we were forced to leave them as we found them in their Sins.</p>
               <p n="3">3. God will be juſtified in their <hi>Condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation,</hi> to whom his Precepts and Promiſes avail nothing. To entertain ſuch gracious Offers with ſuch ſhameful Contempt, is a Sin which cannot be revenged with exceſſive Severity. If any of you did but make a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Tryal, and God would not receive you when you come to him, you might have a Plea for your going back again; but when God comes forth to you with Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in his Hand, and Compaſſion in his Heart, you that never tryed can have no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to ſay for ſleighting it.</p>
               <p n="4">4. The Devil can lay no blocks in our Way againſt our coming unto God, but what we may eaſily remove or couragiouſly leap over, if we look no further than this Text. Hath not God warranted our coming by his <hi>Precept,</hi> and encouraged it by his <hi>Promiſe?</hi> Hath he not commanded us to return, and engaged to heal us? What would we have him to ſay which he hath not ſaid?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Obj.</hi> If I were ſure he were <hi>my God</hi> I would come.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1. If thou <hi>deſireſt</hi> that he ſhould be <hi>thine,</hi> if thou <hi>chooſeſt</hi> him to be <hi>thine,</hi> he is ſo.</p>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:51055:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <p n="2">2. If thou <hi>Conſenteſt</hi> to be <hi>his,</hi> he is un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubtedly <hi>thine.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. Though thou canſt not regularly claim him as <hi>thine,</hi> while thou art at a diſtance from him, yet <hi>in thy coming,</hi> thou mayſt lay thy Claim. There is a Propriety and Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt in God transferred to Thee in that ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Moment.</p>
               <p n="5">5. How unreaſonable would it be, if any of the Storms we meet with in our Way to God, ſhould ever drive us back, or ſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wrack our Faith! When <hi>Peter</hi> was coming to Chriſt upon the Water, the Wind grew boiſterous, and he began to ſink, but Chriſt caught him and ſaved him.</p>
               <p>So when we are upon our Return to God, 'tis no wonder if we find Diſturbance and Oppoſition, and a great many things to pull us back, and ſcare us from going forwards. The Maſter whom we have ſerved ſo many Years is unwilling to part with us, and therefore will create all the difficulties, and repreſent the utmoſt dangers which he can; but Gods good and comfortable Word ſhould weigh down all: And when ſo many have done well, why ſhould any one of us ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine that he ſhall be <hi>the firſt rejected Perſon?</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="6">6. How Happy would it be, if the <hi>Effi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cacy</hi> of this Doctrine were equal to the <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernment</hi> of it! It extends to <hi>All</hi> that are born into the World, and therefore ſhould operate upon all likewiſe. All <hi>Adams</hi> Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterity are a brood of Backſliders, vile A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtate Creatures, that have univerſally
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:51055:15"/>gone aſide, and ſtraggled and wandered from God, and therefore all are bound with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Diſtinction, to agree and joyn in this dutiful Profeſſion, <hi>Behold we come unto thee.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If this whole Aſſembly would Eccho ſo to this Sermon, it would be the moſt joyful ſound that ever I heard. The Spirit and the Word this Day ſay come; and if every one that heareth did alſo ſay, <hi>Lo I come,</hi> it would be the beſt Sabbath that ever I ſaw. Not that it is enough to ſay, <hi>we come,</hi> unleſs we do it; he that ſaid <hi>I go and went not,</hi> ſtood condemned out of his own Mouth, <hi>Mat.</hi> 21.30.</p>
               <p>But ſuch Words accompanied with our Hearts, and accompliſht in our Practice, are the beſt which can be uttered by any Tongue on Earth.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="sermon">
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:51055:15"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>SERMON II.</hi> Of Eſtabliſhment.</head>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>ACTS XI. 23. latter part.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                     <p>And exhorted them all, that with purpoſe of Heart, they would cleave unto the Lord.</p>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>IT is no ſmall Inſtance of the Wiſdom of Providence, that God hath always o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver-ruled the Malice of the Devil, to be a means of accompliſhing the Deſigns of his own Grace: About the Time of <hi>Stephens</hi> Death, (who was the <hi>firſt Martyr</hi> in the New Teſtament Church) there aroſe ſo violent a Storm of Perſecution, that it diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſt the Church which was at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and only the Apoſtles were left to keep Poſſeſſion for Chriſt of the Goſpel there; but this happen'd to the furtherance of that, which Satan intended to ſtifle and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct; for they that were ſcattered abroad, <hi>Went every where Preaching the Word,</hi> Chap. 8.4. We find ſome of this number arrived at <hi>Antioch,</hi> ver. 19, 20. of this Chapter, and they had great ſucceſs in their Work there,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:51055:16"/>for <hi>the Hand of the Lord was with them,</hi> a Divine Power accompanied their Miniſtry, and Multitudes believed, and turned to the Lord, <hi>ver.</hi> 21. The Church at <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> hearing of this, take care to ſend <hi>Barnabas</hi> thither, <hi>ver.</hi> 22. A Man whom the Apoſtles gave that Name to, which ſignifies, <hi>a Son of Conſolation,</hi> Chap. 4.36. And a Man of Note and good Reputation among the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles, as appears <hi>Chap.</hi> 9.27. And one that hath an excellent Character here, <hi>ver.</hi> 24. <hi>A good Man and full of the Holy Choſt, and of Faith.</hi> This is the Man that is diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patcht to theſe Chriſtians at <hi>Antioch,</hi> and this, <hi>ver.</hi> 23. gives us an Account of the Iſſue of his coming, <hi>Who when he came, and had ſeen the Grace of God, was glad, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horted them all, that with purpoſe of Heart, they would cleave unto the Lord.</hi> The whole may be ſum'd up, under three General Heads.</p>
               <p n="1">1. What he ſaw <hi>[and had ſeen the Grace of God]</hi> that is, the viſible Fruits and Ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects of it, in their Holy Converſation and Godlineſs, and whereſoever the Grace of God is truly planted and deeply rooted in the Heart, it will diſcover and evidence it ſelf by ſuitable Workings in the Life: 'Tis a Seed which will ſpring up, a Light which will ſhine, and a Fire which will flame, more or leſs, to the view of others.</p>
               <p n="2">2. How he was affected with what he ſaw <hi>[was glad.]</hi> he did not Envy or Repine, but Rejoice. The ſucceſsful progreſs of the Goſpel, and ſaving Efficacy upon thoſe that
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:51055:16"/>hear it, is Matter of Joy to Holy Souls. It is a mighty Addition to their own Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, when they ſee others brought home to God by the Word. The encreaſe of the Body is acceptable to all the Members.</p>
               <p n="3">3. His Exhortation grounded hereupon. <hi>[And exhorted them all that with purpoſe of Heart, they would cleave unto the Lord.]</hi> There are three Particulars in this.</p>
               <p n="1">1. The Act <hi>Cleave,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, which ſome render continue or abide in; the Senſe of both is the ſame.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The Object, <hi>to the Lord.</hi> That is, to Chriſt, who is uſually to be underſtood by that Title in the New Teſtament.</p>
               <p n="3">3. The Manner, <hi>with purpoſe of Heart.</hi> The ſame Word which we tranſlate Purpoſe here, is uſed to expreſs the Eternal and Immutable Decree of God, concerning the Salvation of his Elect, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.28. <hi>Eph.</hi> 3.11. 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.9.</p>
               <p>Obſ. <hi>Reſolved cleaving to Chriſt, or clea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving with purpoſe of Heart is the proper and neceſſary Duty of thoſe that are al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready Converted to him.</hi> Here,
<list>
                     <item>1. Shew, how we are to cleave to Chriſt.</item>
                     <item>2. What it is to do this, with purpoſe of Heart.</item>
                     <item>3. Why is this the Duty of all that are Converted to him.</item>
                     <item>4. Uſe.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:51055:17"/>
               <p n="1">I. <hi>How are we to cleave to Christ?</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. We muſt cleave <hi>to the Perſon of Chriſt,</hi> by a continued Life of <hi>Faith</hi> upon him. Thus <hi>Hezekiah</hi> truſted in the Lord God of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and in that reſpect is ſaid to <hi>cleave to him,</hi> 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 18.5, 6. This is the Foundation Grace, and the daily Exerciſe of it is highly requiſite. Beſides, our firſt receiving of Chriſt whereby we are united to him, we muſt be often renewing our Applications to Chriſt, and Dependencies upon him. As the Traitor <hi>Judas,</hi> when he gave that Sign to the Officers, <hi>Whomſoever I ſhall Kiſs, that ſame is he,</hi> bid them to <hi>hold him faſt,</hi> Mat. 26.48. So it may be ſaid to all thoſe that have apprehended Chriſt, and are appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended of him, <hi>hold him Faſt;</hi> take freſh hold, and further hold of him every Day. The Faith of Adherence and Recumbence muſt be acted, whatever Circumſtances we be in; whether clear or cloudy, calm or ſtormy.</p>
               <p>There are two Conſiderations which ſhould enforce this with us,</p>
               <p n="1">1. The miſchievous workings of <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nbelief</hi> in our own Hearts. This Infirmity ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times prevails too much, where there is the greateſt Strength of Grace. Eminent Saints that have been lifted up to the Heaven of Aſſurance, have fallen from thence almoſt (though not altogether) into the Hell of Deſpair; they that have triumpht in Chriſt,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:51055:17"/>and thought their Intereſt in him paſt all Queſtion, have been ready afterwards to renounce all their Conſidence and Comfort, as Men aſhamed of their Hope. This ſhews how the Leproſie of <hi>Infidelity</hi> cleaves to us like a ſtubborn Diſeaſe, and will be breaking out, unleſs we are careful to keep it under by conſtant actual Believing.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The ſubtle and dangerous Inſinuations of the Devil. His buſineſs. is to beat us off from our hold, to looſen us from Chriſt, and perſuade us to let him go. And with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out great Caution and Diligence on our Part, he will get ground upon us: What he cannot do by his Rage, he frequently ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſhes by his Cunning: As the falſe Teachers falſly ſuggeſted to the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> concerning <hi>Paul,</hi> that <hi>being crafty he caught them with Guile,</hi> 2 Cor. 12.16. Satan labours to diſcourage many a Saint, from cleaving to Chriſt by urging that his Iniquities have ſeparated between Chriſt and him; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as no Sin can really ſeparate where Faith unites.</p>
               <p n="2">2. We muſt cleave <hi>to the Truth and Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of Chriſt,</hi> by a ſteady acknowledgment and Profeſſion of them. It is as much our Duty to retain them, as it is to embrace them at the <hi>firſt.</hi> Whe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> God has brought us to the Knowledge of the Truth, as it is in Jeſus; we muſt take heed of being led a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way by contrary Errors. <hi>Errors</hi> in the Plu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral, for they are <hi>manifold,</hi> though <hi>Truth</hi> is but <hi>one,</hi> and this as a ſacred Truſt which is
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:51055:18"/>delivered to the Saints to keep, <hi>Prov.</hi> 23.23. <hi>Buy the Truth and Sell it not.</hi> We are to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour the getting of it by all the Means we can; but not to part with it at any Rate, or upon any Terms whatever. The Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of Chriſt in all the Branches of it, ought to be precious to us, as well as Chriſt himſelf. As the Fragments of a Miraculous Entertainment, ſo the leaſt parts of Divine Revelation are not to be loſt. If the whole Counſel of God was worthy of his decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, 'tis worthy of our aſſerting. It was the Commendation which Chriſt gave to the church in <hi>Pergamos,</hi> Rev. 2.13. <hi>Thou holdeſt faſt my Name, and haſt not denied my Faith,</hi> (with this remarkable Circumſtance) <hi>even in thoſe Days wherein Antipas my faithful Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyr was ſlain among you.</hi> So to the Church in <hi>Philadelphia; Thou haſt kept my Word, and haſt not denyed my Name;</hi> though ſhe had but a little Strength, yet it was well impro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, <hi>Chap.</hi> 3.8. If the Name, and World, and Faith of Chriſt be relinquiſhed by us, we do really abandon <hi>him;</hi> we cannot ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>here to him, and give up any thing that is his, that hath been revealed and taught by him, or by thoſe that were ſent by him, or any thing that carries his Mark and Impreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion upon it.</p>
               <p n="3">3. We muſt cleave <hi>to the Ways of Chriſt;</hi> that is, <hi>his Commandments</hi> and <hi>Ordinances.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. To his Commandments by ſtrict Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience. In this Senſe we find <hi>cleaving to God</hi> ſeveral Times enjoyned, <hi>Deut.</hi> 11.22.
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:51055:18"/>and 13.4. <hi>Joſh.</hi> 22.5. All Divine Precepts as they have a never failing Authority, ought to have an abiding influence; They are a fixed Rule, and they challenge our ſetled regard. <hi>Bind them continually upon thine Heart,</hi> Prov. 6.21. They ſhould be ever with us, and ever before us. They are not to be obſerved now and then, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed at one Time, and neglected at another; but we are to walk in <hi>them at all times;</hi> and at no Time to go back from them. This ſuits with the honourable Character which <hi>Paul</hi> gives of his <hi>Philippi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi> Chap. 2.12. <hi>You have always obeyed.</hi> They that do not make Conſcience of obey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>always,</hi> are truly Children of diſobedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence; if we are <hi>under a Law to Chriſt,</hi> we can never imagine our ſelves to be <hi>with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Law to God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. To his <hi>Ordinances,</hi> by a Religious uſe of them in their various Seaſons. And thus cleaving to God is ſometimes preſt with re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect to Matters of <hi>Worſhip,</hi> and in Oppoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to ſtrange Gods, <hi>Dent.</hi> 10.20. <hi>Joſh.</hi> 23.7, 8. We do not indeed cleave to Chriſt, if we forſake any Inſtitution of Chriſt, and take up with any Invention of Men. We muſt cleave to him as <hi>the Lord over his own Houſe,</hi> inveſted with Soveraign and incommunica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Power, to diſpoſe and order whatſoever ſhall be done in it. The diſuſe of any Holy Appointment of his, is a degree of Apoſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy from the Author They that have So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnly given up themſelves, and their Names
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:51055:19"/>to Chriſt, by perſonal Covenanting with him at his Table, are eſpecially Guilty in this Caſe, if they afterwards withdraw from it, or attend it uncertainly. It argues great forgetfulneſs of Chriſt, and our Engagements unto him, not to do that ſtatedly in Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance of him.</p>
               <p n="4">4. We muſt cleave <hi>to the People of Chriſt.</hi> He directs his Spouſe to <hi>go forth by the Foot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteps of the Flock,</hi> Song 1.8. Not to follow them afar off, but to joyn and aſſociate with them and never to quit, or divide from them. They vainly hope to enjoy Communion with Chriſt, that leave the Communion of Saints, <hi>Zech.</hi> 8.23. <hi>Ten Men out of the Languages of all Nations, ſhall take hold of the Skirt of a Jew, ſaying, we will go with you, for we have heard that God is with you.</hi> It ſeems to be a Goſpel Prophecy dreſt up in Old Teſtament Phraſes, and refers to the embodying of the <hi>Gentiles</hi> with the Chriſtian Church. The pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiar Preſence of Chriſt is with his People, and they go out from that preſence, that ſeparate themſelves from that People. We muſt not do like the <hi>Samaritans</hi> of old, who were wont to own a Relation to the <hi>Jews</hi> in their Proſperity, and diſclaimed it in their Adverſity; but whatſoever their External Condition be, the living Temples of God are to be preferred to all the gaudy and pompous Synagogues of Satan. <hi>Moſes</hi> his choice of ſuffering Affliction with the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of God: <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.25. Is a Pattern to us, if they wander in Deſerts, in Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:51055:19"/>in Dens and Caves of the Earth, 'tis beſt to be with them. Where they go and lodge we ſhould alſo, as we deſire that their God ſhould be our God.</p>
               <p n="2">II. <hi>What is it to cleave to Chriſt with pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe of Heart?</hi> I Anſwer in three Things.</p>
               <p n="1">1. It implies a deliberate Act of the <hi>Judgment. Every</hi> rational <hi>Purpoſe is eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by Counſel,</hi> Prov. 20.18. It is founded upon Reaſon, or elſe we may expect it to be diſappointed and overthrown. He that reſolvedly cleaves to Chriſt, is firſt ſuppoſed to ſit down, and ſeriouſly conſider why he does ſo; for if he be not convinc't that he ought to do it, and if he do not proceed to reſolve upon thoſe grounds, all will come to nothing. Therefore when the King of <hi>Babylon</hi> out of his peculiar Favour to ſome of the Children of the Captivity, appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed them a daily Proviſion of his meat and Wine, 'tis ſaid that the Prophet <hi>Daniel pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed in his Heart, that he would not defile him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf with the Portion of the Kings Meat, nor with the Wine which he drank,</hi> Dan. 1.8. This was not obſtinacy or humor in him, or a fooliſh ſtiffneſs without a Cauſe, for he had weighed the Matter and found that he could not do it without Pollution; For <hi>Firſt,</hi> The <hi>Babylonians</hi> freely eat of many Things for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden to the <hi>Jews. Secondly,</hi> 'Tis probable that many Times they eat of things offered to their Idols. <hi>Thirdly,</hi> Such riotous living
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:51055:20"/>and pampering of the Fleſh, could not be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſed from Sin at any Time. <hi>Fourthly,</hi> It was much more unbecoming any of the Seed of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> in their preſent Circumſtances in a ſtrange Land. Thus <hi>Daniel</hi>'s <hi>Purpoſe</hi> to abſtain was an Act of <hi>Judgment,</hi> upon due Deliberation with himſelf; ſo muſt our pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe of continuing with Chriſt be; that we may do it with all our Mind, and with all our Underſtanding.</p>
               <p n="2">2. It includes a determinate Act of the <hi>Will:</hi> When after debating of the Thing in our own Thoughts, we come to a final Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſue, the Will gives poſitive Sentence that it ſhall be ſo. This is called <hi>decreeing in the Heart,</hi> 1 Cor. 7.37. Thus <hi>David</hi> ſays, <hi>I am purpoſed that my Mouth ſhall not Tranſgreſs,</hi> Pſalm 17.3. Which we have in other words, <hi>Pſalm</hi> 39.1. <hi>I ſaid, I will take heed to my Ways, that I Sin not with my Tongue,</hi> &amp;c. To ſay in our Hearts, that we will do this, or that, is indeed to Purpoſe it. He that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolves in good earneſt is no longer in ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence, whether he ſhould or ſhould not; he does not hang like an even Ballance, or halt between two. Thus muſt we cleave to Chriſt, with Hearts fully ſet in us ſo to do; as that <hi>Scribe</hi> pretended when he came to <hi>Christ,</hi> and ſaid, <hi>Maſter I will follow thee, whitherſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever thou goest,</hi> Mat. 8.19. If thoſe Words had been more adviſedly ſpoken, they had been well ſpoken, but by our Lords Anſwer, <hi>verſe</hi> 20. It ſhould ſeem as if he knew not what he ſaid; that he dreamt of better Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commodation
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:51055:20"/>than Chriſt had. If we are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termined to follow Chriſt, the bent of the Soul muſt be towards him.</p>
               <p n="3">3. It takes in <hi>an unwearied purſuit</hi> of what we do reſolve. All Purpoſes which are not duly executed, but eaſily broke off, are inſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nificant. This argues Levity of Spirit, and is ſtiled <hi>purpoſing according to the Fleſh,</hi> 2 Cor. 1.17. Carnal Hearts never reſolve any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe in Religious Matters; and in Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Things we may reſolve, and yet change our Intentions without Sin. We are not neceſſarily obliged to do all that we ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times ſay we will do; if we find Reaſon af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards to revoke our Purpoſe, and alter our Minds, as 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 15.26. <hi>Samuel</hi> ſaid to <hi>Saul, I will not return with thee,</hi> yet <hi>ver.</hi> 31. we read that <hi>he returned again after Saul.</hi> But now in this Caſe, of cleaving to Chriſt, our Purpoſe admits of no Revocati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. There is as much Reaſon for our final perſiſting in it, as for our firſt Agreement to it. <hi>That</hi> was vain and needleſs, if <hi>this</hi> be ſo. Our Thoughts with reſpect to this Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſhould be as truly unmoveable in our mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, as Gods are; of whom 'tis ſaid, <hi>He is of one Mind, and who can turn him,</hi> Job 23.13.</p>
               <p n="3">III. <hi>Why is this the Duty of all, that are Converted to Christ, to cleave reſolvedly to him?</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. The <hi>Sincerity</hi> of our <hi>Affection</hi> muſt be
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:51055:21"/>proved by the <hi>Stedfaſtneſs</hi> of our <hi>Adherence.</hi> 'Tis a ſign that we did but make a ſhew of cloſing with Chriſt, except we keep cloſe to him. Which way ſoever our Faces ſtood, 'tis certain that our Hearts were never right, if we can be by any means influenced to turn our backs upon God again. They that at any Time wholly <hi>fail of the Grace of God,</hi> never knew it <hi>in Truth.</hi> Your Converſion was but a feigned thing, or you could not be guilty of a total Revolt, <hi>Heb.</hi> 3.6. <hi>Whoſe Houſe are we, if we hold faſt the Confidence, and rejoycing of Hope firm unto the End.</hi> All that are an Habitation for Chriſt, are di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſhed by this Token; lively Stones have ſuch a Conjunction with the Head of the Corner, that they cannot drop out of the Building. Branches that are in Chriſt by re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Union, always abide in Chriſt, and Chriſt in them; but others wither and dye, and fall off from him. That Profeſſion which is not crowned with Perſeverance, is tainted with Hypocriſie; for they that come to Chriſt in the uprightneſs of their Souls, cannot break away from him.</p>
               <p n="2">2. 'Tis <hi>baſe Ingratitude</hi> to ſhake off <hi>Chriſt,</hi> who is ſo true and faithful to you. His for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſakings of you are never but in Appearance only, His Promiſe is ſure; <hi>I will never leave thee nor forſake thee,</hi> Heb. 13.5. He is with Believers always, but ſometimes hid and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>known, ſo that they diſcern him not; but if he were not with them, the whole Work of God would ceaſe, and be deſtroyed immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately.
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:51055:21"/>He is careful to ſupply the want of his bodily Preſence, by his Spirit, whom he not only promiſed to ſend, but engaged for his Abode with us for ever, <hi>John</hi> 14.16. He does not call back this Spirit, when you ſinfully grieve him, nor deliver you up to your own Luſts, when you provoke him ſo to do. He holds you in his hand ſtill, when there are Legions of Devils banded together, to pluck you out; and do you thus requite him, to wreſt your ſelves out? 'Tis too foul a Thing to be done by any of thoſe, that are <hi>truly his;</hi> but they that <hi>are not,</hi> will reward his greateſt kindneſs, at one Time or other with the vileſt Treachery.</p>
               <p n="3">3. If you do not cleave to Chriſt, <hi>you let go all your Happineſs at once.</hi> As <hi>Moſes</hi> ſaid to <hi>Iſrael,</hi> Deut. 30.20. <hi>That thou mayſt cleave to him, for he is thy Life, and the length of thy Days,</hi> q. d. You are dead Men if you depart from him, he had given them an Inſtance of this, <hi>Chap.</hi> 4.3, 4. <hi>All the Men that fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed Baal-peor, the Lord thy God hath deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed them from among you; but you that did cleave unto him are alive every one of you this Day.</hi> We are no longer ſafe than we abide with God; aſſoon as we leave him, we ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe our ſelves to them utmoſt Miſery, in that very Moment. Therefore when many Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples went back, and he put it to the Twelve, <hi>Will ye alſo go away? Peter</hi> makes an excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Anſwer, <hi>Lord, to whom ſhall we go? thou haſt the Words of Eternal Life,</hi> John 6.67, 68. <hi>q. d.</hi> What we have left to follow thee,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:51055:22"/>was leſs than nothing, but if we ſhould for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake thee, we muſt Part with more than all; we who have counted every Thing but loſs for thee, can reckon nothing to be gain without thee.</p>
               <p n="4">4. The <hi>longer</hi> you cleave to Chriſt, <hi>the more pleaſant</hi> it will be, and at the cloſe of all, it will be impoſſible to repent your Choice; while you are following on to know the Lord, you will find cauſe to like your Way the better; and the improving of your acquaintance with Chriſt, will encreaſe your Delight in him. Go to thoſe that have had moſt <hi>Experience</hi> of the Grace of Chriſt, to old Diſciples that have had their ſtanding in Chriſt, for the largeſt number of Years, and they will tell you, that they are ſtill every Day further off, from repenting that they were added to the Lord and to the Church. The ſeeming grievouſneſs of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious Duties wears away, when the Heart comes to be exerciſed in them. Chriſts Yoke grows eaſier and ſmoother, when we have born it upon us; though perhaps at the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry firſt putting on, the Fleſh will ſtrive hard to fling it off.</p>
               <p n="5">5. Reſolution in cleaving to Chriſt, will carry you through <hi>all thoſe Diffculties</hi> which affright and deter an <hi>unreſolvedly Man. Ruths</hi> cleaving to <hi>Naomi,</hi> when her Siſter <hi>Orpah</hi> returned to her People and her Gods, and notwithſtanding <hi>Naomi</hi>'s Perſwaſions to her to return, ſhewed her to be inflexible, and made <hi>Naomi</hi> ſilent, <hi>Ruth</hi> 1.18. <hi>When
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:51055:22"/>ſhe ſaw that ſhe was ſtedfaſtly minded to go with her, then ſhe left ſpeaking to here:</hi> So here, if Satan find us wavering and yielding, he will preſs the more upon us, till he hath compaſt his Deſign; but if we ſtand unſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken againſt repeated Temptations, and keep our ground, it will be a diſcouragement to the Tempter; a weakning of his Hands, and a ſtrengthening of our own. <hi>Reſiſt the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil and he will flee from you,</hi> James 4.7. But how muſt he be reſiſted? <hi>Stedfaſt in the Faith,</hi> 1 Pet. 5.9.</p>
               <p n="6">6. The <hi>Time</hi> of <hi>Tryal</hi> and <hi>Exerciſe</hi> is <hi>ſhort,</hi> and the <hi>Reward</hi> is <hi>near;</hi> this makes it ſo much the more your Duty to hold out. You are not to ſpend your Eternity at ſuch a diſtance from Chriſt, as you now are; you are not to tarry very long in the Devils reach, yet a little while and all the danger will be over; you will hear no more of theſe helliſh Sollicitations to depart from Chriſt, when you come to Heaven; and then will feel no more of thoſe wretched (re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maining) Propenſions to it, which now you do. Be but <hi>faithful unto Death</hi> (which may not be very far off) and Death will tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlate you where Chriſt is, and all his perfect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Saints with him. Let none take away your Crown now, and they cannot do it then. Cleave to Chriſt while you are in this Tabernacle, and you'l go out of it with HO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and Triumph. As <hi>David</hi> prayed and pleaded, <hi>Pſalm</hi> 119.31. <hi>I have ſtuck to thy Teſtimonies, Oh Lord! put me not to ſhame.</hi>
                  <pb n="36" facs="tcp:51055:23"/>IV. Uſe.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Learn hence, that the <hi>Foundation</hi> which Men lay at the <hi>beginning</hi> of their <hi>Way,</hi> needs to be <hi>well examined,</hi> that it may bear what is to be built upon it. I do not mean that we ſhould always be calling our firſt Work into queſtion, or making a doubt of it at every turn; but that we ought to make it ſure by ſtrict Examination and Enquiry; and whatever defects we diſcover, which are eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſential, they ought to be mended before we go any further. It is good to proceed upon a ſound bottom, or elſe we ſhall not pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed far enough to attain what we hope for. If we take but a ſuperficial hold of Chriſt, when we enter our ſelves his Diſciples, we ſhall not perſeveringly cleave to him.</p>
               <p n="2">2. All the Work which we have to do, is not done <hi>at firſt,</hi> how well ſoever that be done. <hi>The end of a thing is better than the beginning,</hi> Feel. 7.8. And this we muſt have a careful reſpect to. The new born Soul is not to take its eaſe, or neglect its watch, to be careleſs or ſlothful, but to be employed with all its might, till its grown up to abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute Perfection. <hi>Wiſdom is a Tree of Life to them that lay hold upon her,</hi> (but 'tis immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately added) and <hi>happy is every one that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taineth her,</hi> Prov. 3.18. So <hi>get Wiſdom and forget it not,</hi> Chap. 4.5. That which is loſt again, is worſe than if it had never been poſſeſt at all.</p>
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:51055:23" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <p n="3">3. The <hi>Miniſters of Chriſt</hi> have a great deal of <hi>eſtabliſhing,</hi> as well as <hi>converting Work</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on their Hands. <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Barnabas,</hi> when they came to <hi>Antioch</hi> in another Journey, ſpake to thoſe that followed them and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuaded them <hi>to continue in the Grace of God,</hi> Acts 13.43. So at another Time, when they returned to the Cities where they had preacht the Goſpel before, they confirmed the Souls of the Diſciples, and exhorted them <hi>to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue in the Faith,</hi> Chap. 14.22. Our buſineſs lies with Saints as well as Sinners; <hi>Propheſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſerveth not for them that believe not</hi> (only) <hi>but for them which believe</hi> (alſo) 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.22. We dye in Travel if Chriſt be not form<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in you; and we cannot live, except they that are brought home, do <hi>ſtand faſt in the Lord.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. <hi>Effectual Religious Parpoſes are of extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary Importance.</hi> I ſay effectual; for as they will not ſuffice, where the deed may be, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.11. So Reſolution without A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction will not be accepted: For it is not ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious and hearty, <hi>Pſalm</hi> 119.106. <hi>I have ſaorn and will perform it,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p n="2">2. How ſhall we do that <hi>our Purpoſes</hi> in cleaving to Chriſt, may be <hi>Effectual.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1. <hi>Reſolve not</hi> in your <hi>own Strength;</hi> then you will certainly fail and miſcarry, to puniſh your Preſumption and expoſe your Weakneſs. Say with the Pſalmiſt, <hi>I will go in the ſtrength of the Lord God,</hi> Pſalm 71.16.</p>
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:51055:24"/>
               <p n="2">2. Let your <hi>Ends</hi> and <hi>Motives</hi> be <hi>right:</hi> Cleave to the Lord for his own ſake; fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low him not for the Loaves of temporal Advantages, leſt they ſhould abate and va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh. The Purity of our Aims, will conduce to the Stability of our Purpoſes.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Keep up an <hi>high Valuation</hi> and <hi>Eſteem</hi> of <hi>Christ;</hi> ſpiritual Beings are cemented by Love, ſo as to be inſeparable, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 18.1. The Soul of <hi>Jonathan</hi> was knit to the Soul of <hi>David,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Shechems</hi> Soul clave to <hi>Dinah,</hi> ſo that he would agree to any Terms upon her Account, <hi>Gen.</hi> 34.3. with 12.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Labour after an <hi>encreaſed Senſe</hi> of the <hi>odiouſneſs</hi> of <hi>Sin.</hi> Rom. 12.9. <hi>Abbor that which is Evil, cleave to that which is good.</hi> They are well coupled, for the more loath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome <hi>the one</hi> is, that more Tenacious ſhall we be of <hi>the other.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="5">5. Sit <hi>looſe</hi> from <hi>the World,</hi> and its en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tangling <hi>Enjoyments.</hi> The greater hold they take of us, the more apt and liable are we to be removed from Chriſt. <hi>Solomon</hi> clave to ſtrange Women in Love, and they turned away his Heart from God, 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 11.2, 3.</p>
               <p n="6">6. Let <hi>no Example</hi> have any influence up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on you, which is againſt <hi>the Rule.</hi> When every Man of <hi>Iſrael</hi> went up from after <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid,</hi> and followed <hi>Sheba,</hi> the Men of <hi>Judah</hi> ſtill <hi>clave to their King,</hi> 2 Sam. 20.2. If you could ſuppoſe Chriſt univerſally renounc't, and your ſelves left <hi>alone</hi> in adherence to him, it would be <hi>your Glory</hi> to be <hi>Singular,</hi> and to <hi>abide Faithful.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="sermon">
               <pb n="39" facs="tcp:51055:24"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>SERMON III.</hi> Of Conſolation.</head>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>MAT. XXVIII. 5.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                     <p>And the Angel anſwered, and ſaid unto the Women, Fear not ye: For I know that ye ſeek JES<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S which was Crucified.</p>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>THE foregoing Chapter gives us a large Account of the Death and Burial of Jeſus Chriſt, and of the Care which his E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies took to keep him faſt in the Priſon of the Grave; but this could not be done, for the Morning of the third Day after his De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaſe, which was <hi>the firſt Day of the Week,</hi> was the appointed Time of his Reſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Accordingly, when this Morning came, the Earth was ſhaken and gave up its Dead, and an Angel was diſpatcht from Heaven, to roll away the Stone from the Door of the Sepulchre, <hi>ver.</hi> 2 of this Chap. This An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gel when he had removed the Stone, had not done all his Buſineſs, but went and ſat
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:51055:25"/>upon it, and appeared in ſuch an awful man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, that the Keepers who were ſet to watch, trembled at the ſight of him; like Men amazed and utterly diſpirited, <hi>ver.</hi> 3, 4. Yea it ſeems that not only they, but the Holy Women alſo (mentioned, <hi>ver.</hi> 1.) who came with a better deſign to ſee the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulchre, aſſoon as the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Sabbath was over, were through the Infirmity of their Fleſh (though not like the Keepers, through guilt of Conſcience) under ſome diſcompo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing Terror. As the Diſciples themſelves, when they heard the Voice out of the Cloud in the Mount of Tranſfiguration, were ſore afraid, <hi>Mat.</hi> 17.6. So if theſe Women had not been exerciſed with timorous uneaſie Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſions now, thoſe comfortable Words which are ſpoken to them here in the Text, would have been altogether needleſs. Which I have the rather choſen at this Time to <hi>Diſcourſe</hi> on; not only becauſe they may ſeem to have ſome <hi>Reference</hi> to the <hi>Ordinance</hi> of the <hi>Lord Supper</hi> which is to follow; but alſo as the fitteſt I know of to <hi>Connect</hi> with my two Laſt <hi>Diſcourſes;</hi> the <hi>Firſt</hi> was on <hi>Converſion,</hi> the <hi>Second</hi> on <hi>Eſtabliſhment;</hi> therefore I ſhall <hi>now</hi> add a <hi>Third</hi> on <hi>Conſola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion;</hi> and if I do by the <hi>Bleſſing</hi> of <hi>God</hi> ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain my <hi>End</hi> in theſe <hi>Sermons, <hi>I need Preach no more.</hi>
                  </hi>
               </p>
               <p>In theſe Words we may conſider theſe four Things.</p>
               <pb n="41" facs="tcp:51055:25"/>
               <p n="1">1. The Perſon ſpeaking, <hi>And the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gel anſwered and ſaid;</hi> thoſe miniſtring Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits are very ready, to deliver any reviving Meſſages to the Heirs of Salvation, that wherein they can they may be, the helpers of their Joy; as to <hi>Zacharias,</hi> Luke 1.13. to <hi>Paul,</hi> Acts 27.24.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The Perſons applied to <hi>[to the Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men,]</hi> who ſignalized their Affection to Chriſt, by attending his Laſt Sufferings, and by preparing Oyntments and Spices for his Dead Body, and by their early Viſits at his Grave. As they loved more than others ſo they're favour'd more than others, with the firſt joyful Tidings of the Reſurrection of Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
               <p n="3">3. The encouraging Matter <hi>[Fear not Ye]</hi> There is a ſpecial Emphaſis upon that word <hi>Ye,</hi> q. d. Let the Centinels whoſe work it is to Guard the Sepulchre be af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frighted, if they will; but there is no ſuch Cauſe for your being ſo: I have no Conſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation to impart to them, but to <hi>you</hi> I have.</p>
               <p n="4">4. The ſatisfying Reaſon <hi>[For I know that ye ſeek Jeſus, who was Crucified.</hi>] Though it be Gods peculiar Perfection to know the Hearts of his Creatures, 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 8.39. Yet we may know very much of the Thoughts and Intentions of others by their Actions and Deportments; and ſo the Angel might be able to ſay, he knew by the Circumſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of the Womens coming hither, what it was they came about, and whom they en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired after.</p>
               <pb n="42" facs="tcp:51055:26"/>
               <p>Obſ. <hi>Where any Souls do truly deſign the ſeeking of a Crucified Jeſus, all diſquiet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing fear must needs be groundleſs; and not a Duty, but a Fault, 'tis not that they are call'd to, but warned against.</hi> Here,
<list>
                     <item>1. I ſhall ſhew, <hi>Who they are</hi> that truly deſign the ſeeking of a <hi>Crucified Jeſus.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>2. <hi>Why</hi> all diſquieting Fears in ſuch, muſt be groundleſs.</item>
                     <item>3. <hi>Whence</hi> theſe Fears ariſe.</item>
                     <item>4. <hi>
                           <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p n="1">I. <hi>Who they are,</hi> that truly deſign the ſeeking of <hi>a Crucified Jeſus?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Anſwer in ſix Things.</p>
               <p n="1">1. They that ſeriouſly look upon <hi>Christ</hi> as <hi>moſt worthy to be ſought,</hi> and <hi>neceſſary to be found;</hi> and are therefore willing to neglect or abandon all other Things whatſoever for the ſake of him. There are none that ſeek him in good Earneſt, but ſuch as this Character is applicable to; we muſt be,</p>
               <p n="1">1. Deeply convinc't, that nothing elſe doth ſo well <hi>deſerve</hi> our Pains in ſeeking it; nor is there ſuch an abſolute and indiſpenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble <hi>Neceſſity</hi> of finding it. We may be poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſt of all other Things without Chriſt, and yet be miſerable; we may miſs or fail of all other Things, and yet be Happy in Chriſt <hi>Whoſo findeth him, findeth Life,</hi> &amp;c.
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:51055:26"/>
                  <hi>Prov.</hi> 8.35. He is the <hi>one Thing needful,</hi> and the one Thing to be deſired; unleſs there be a ſound and ſetled Conviction of this, there can be no Sincerity.</p>
               <p n="2">2. We muſt be fully reſolved to paſs o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, and to relinquiſh every Thing in the World <hi>for Christs ſake.</hi> They that chooſe rather to omit a ſeaſon of Converſe with Chriſt, than the Proſecution of a ſecular Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fair, have Reaſon to be Jealous of their own Hypocriſie. <hi>Martha</hi> had a ſharp rebuke for ſpending her Time about the Entertainment of Chriſt, when ſhe ſhould with her Siſter have been hearing of him. Chriſt muſt be diligently ſought, though all be forſaken in Order to it.</p>
               <p n="2">2. They that <hi>make uſe of all the appointed Means,</hi> and providential <hi>Opportunities,</hi> of <hi>finding Christ,</hi> which are put into their Hands. He that conſcientiouſly uſes <hi>any one,</hi> will thankfully embrace them <hi>all;</hi> for as the ſame Authority binds to, ſo the ſame good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs furniſhes with, all alike. Whereſoever Chriſt hath been, or is to be found, we are to ſeek him; there is a variety of Divine Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances, all tending to the ſame Purpoſe, <hi>viz.</hi> Fellowſhip with Chriſt, but none of them are to be diſuſed. We ſhould follow Chriſt from one Ordinance to another, as the zealous Multitude did from Place to Place. <hi>When our Lord departed privately by Ship to a Deſert Place, the People that knew him ſeeing it, ran a-foot out of all cities, and out-went the Ship, and came together to him,</hi>
                  <pb n="44" facs="tcp:51055:27"/>Mark 6.33. They that have an hearty de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to meet with Chriſt will ſeek him in their Cloſets, and ſeek him in his Sanctuary, and above all at his Table, where his Death is ſolemnly Commemorated. A Crucified Jeſus is there chiefly to be ſought, we contradict our ſelves if we ſay, we would ſee Jeſus, and do not go where he feeds, but avoid the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutions which he is preſent in, and commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicates himſelf by. His Enemies had ſo much Policy as to ſeek him where he frequently reſorted, <hi>John</hi> 18.2, 3.</p>
               <p n="3">3. They that are <hi>not contented</hi> with the <hi>best of Means, unleſs they attain this End;</hi> of the Enjoyment of Chriſt by them. As <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi> notwithſtanding his great reſpect to the Tabernacle, and performance of Publick Worſhip there, carried his Thoughts and Deſires beyond it, to him that filled it with his Glory, <hi>Pſalm</hi> 42.1, 2. <hi>My Soul panteth after thee oh God. My Soul thirſteth for God,</hi> &amp;c. As true Seekers of Jeſus Chriſt, can have no Satisfaction in the bare Hearing of the Word of Chriſt, though an Angel were to Preach it; nor can ſuch an one really Feaſt upon the ſacred Elements which reſpect Chriſt, though the greateſt Apoſtle were now alive to Diſpenſe them. To an Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crite its enough to have the outward Means, and attend upon them; for indeed the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence or abſence of Chriſt is an indifferent Thing to ſuch; but to have ſome ſweet Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience of Divine Communion, or elſe an afflicting Senſe of the want of it, is the Mark
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:51055:27"/>of an unfeigned Believer. Perhaps the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Saint upon Earth hath not always that manifeſt Communion with Chriſt, which he would have; but the leaſt of Saints is great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly troubled and concerned when he hath it not. I will ſay that <hi>Mourning</hi> and <hi>Lamenting after the Lord,</hi> is as ſure a Token of <hi>Integrity,</hi> as the moſt comfortable Enjoyment of him.</p>
               <p n="4">4. They that <hi>hold on in the unwearied Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuits of Christ,</hi> notwithſtanding all Diſcou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragements. They that do not ſeek Chriſt heartily, will quickly ceaſe, and give over ſeeking him. It is ſtrength of Affection which makes us perſevere, and continue in this Work, which otherwiſe would ſoon tire us out. When <hi>Elijah</hi> was ſnatcht up to Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven by a whirlwind, the Sons of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets at <hi>Jericho,</hi> ſuſpecting leſt he ſhould be caſt upon ſome Mountain, or into ſome Val<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ley, were for ending ſifty Men to ſeek him; and urged <hi>Eliſha</hi> for his Conſent, till he was aſhamed to deny them any longer; and ſo the Men went and ſought him three Days, but found him not, 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 2.16, 17. Their reſpect to the Man of God put them upon do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his, as a voluntary act; though they were forbidden, for <hi>Eliſha</hi> had ſaid you ſhall not ſend: How much more earneſt and ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger ſhould we be, in ſeeking after Chriſt, when we are commanded? If we think it our Duty to begin any enquiry or ſearch at all, we cannot but think that 'tis our Sin to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt; even tho he ſeem to flee from us, and to go further off, the faſter we advance to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:51055:28"/>him; though he conceal and hide him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf the more, the nearer we preſs to him.</p>
               <p n="5">5. They which ſteer the ſame Courſe which Chriſt did, and <hi>walk as he walked,</hi> are ſincere Seekers of him. 'Tis a vain pretence to ſay, we are engaged in the purſuit of chriſt, and go a contrary Way; if we would find him out where he is, we muſt undoubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edly tread in his Steps. As ſome quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcented Creatures in hunting after their Prey, will exactly follow the Track, where it hath gone before them; upright Souls ſtrive as much to imitate Chriſt as to enjoy him; and they practice Imitation in order to Fruition. We cannot hope to have our paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage through the World ſweetned with the preſence of Chriſt, unleſs we learn to be as he was in the World. As our Lord Jeſus carried himſelf in all manner of Converſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on towards God, and towards Men, ſo ſhall we do, if our Hearts are ſet aright; becauſe there is no meeting with him out of his own Way. In that very way of filial Obedience wherein Chriſt ſought the honouring and pleaſing of God, we are alſo to ſeek the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proving of our ſelves to Chriſt, and the kind Intimations of Love from him.</p>
               <p n="6">6. They ſeek a Crucified Jeſus indeed, that have an holy Ambition of being <hi>Cruci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied with Christ,</hi> as <hi>Paul</hi> was, <hi>Gal.</hi> 2.20. Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps, there are ſome (too many) in the World, who would be glad to be ſure that Chriſt was Crucified for them, but they are by no means willing to be Crucified with
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:51055:28"/>him: <hi>i. e.</hi> In the Language of the ſame A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle, <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.6. <hi>To have their old Man Cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cified with him;</hi> their Luſts and Corruptions deſtroyed, and put to Death, by Vertue of <hi>his Death.</hi> Now this argues a great deceit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs of Heart, in deſiring ſome Benefit from Chriſt, without any regard to his Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon; <hi>i. e.</hi> ſeeking not <hi>him</hi> but <hi>his.</hi> We diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemble with Chriſt, except we covet to have our Sins drowned in his Blood, as well as to have our Souls wafted to Heaven by it. This is what the Holy Apoſtle aimed at, and preſt after, <hi>To know the Fellowſhip of his Sufferings, and to be made conformable to his Death;</hi> Phil. 3.10. All that are found faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful ſeek to reſemble the Death of Chriſt by <hi>Mortification</hi> now, as well as to reap the Fruit of it in <hi>Glorification</hi> at the laſt.</p>
               <p n="2">II. <hi>Why all diſquieting Fears, in ſuch,</hi> as tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Deſign the ſeeking of Chriſt, <hi>are ground<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs.</hi> I would not be underſtood to ſpeak a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt thoſe humble, reverential, cautious, watchful Fears, which do very week become every Child of God, and ſuit with the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation wherein he ſtands; and the Difficul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, Snares, and Hazards whereby he is yet ſurrounded; but I am to beat down thoſe uncomfortable, reſtleſs, perplexing and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtracting Fears, which are quite of another kind, which are more proper to <hi>Slaves</hi> then <hi>Children,</hi> and which are indeed the Remnants of a <hi>Spirit of Bondage</hi> in Believers. Theſe ought not to be, for Six Reaſons.</p>
               <pb n="48" facs="tcp:51055:29"/>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>This Crucified</hi> Jeſus whom we ſeek, <hi>lives</hi> on our behalf; He Died for us, and now Lives again for us, and Lives for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very; and ſo long as he Lives, we ſhall not Dye. When <hi>Joſeph</hi>'s brethren ſaw that their Father was Dead, they begun to be afraid that their Brother <hi>Joſeph</hi> would now Revenge himſelf upon them, for the Injury they had formerly done to him, <hi>Gen.</hi> 50.15. So if Chriſt had ſeen Corruption, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mained ſtill under the Power of Death, we might have feared, whether he had made ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient Satisfaction in Dying; and whether God might not have proſecuted us notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding. But now this fear is taken away by his Revival; and therefore what ſhould we fear? Chriſt is our living, powerful Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocate with God; and both able and ready to defend us from whatſoever Charge can be brought againſt us. If any ſhould object and ſay, here is Comfort enough in this; if I could be perſwaded and aſſured, that <hi>Chriſt is mine,</hi> and that he lives <hi>for me;</hi> but this I doubt of. I Anſwer in ſhort, thou need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt no other Evidence of thy Propriety, and Intereſt in Chriſt, than thy ſollicitous ſeek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of him, as before deſcribed.</p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>This Jeſus</hi> is graciouſly <hi>near unto us,</hi> or elſe we ſhould not find in our Hearts to ſeek him; our very <hi>Enquirings after him,</hi> are an infallible Proof of <hi>his Preſence with us;</hi> 'tis the Influence of his Spirit which draws out our Souls towards him, which of themſelves are naturally removed very far from him.
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:51055:29"/>Never any Man in the World had the leaſt ſerious Thought of taking one ſtep to find out Chriſt, till the Spirit of Chriſt infuſed that Thought into him. Therefore we have real ſaving Communications from Chriſt, though we have not diſcernable refreſhing Communion with him, which we wiſh and wait for. And he never will nor can for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake us, where he hath once wrought ſuch a Work upon us, of inclining our hearts unto himſelf. Do we then fear that we are yet eſtranged from Chriſt? 'Tis impoſſible, for if ſo, no Account can be given, how we ſhould be prevailed with to do what we do. Do we fear Chriſts future Departings at any Time from us? This is alſo to fear where no fear is; for he adheres more firm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to us than we can to him.</p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>This Jeſus will</hi> certainly <hi>ſupport</hi> and ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtain <hi>us in ſeeking him,</hi> till he is found of us: When like <hi>Gideon's</hi> handful of Soldiers we are faint, yet purſuing, <hi>Judg.</hi> 8.4. He will take Care to Miniſter ſecret Cordials for the relief of our Spirits, in due Meaſure and Seaſon. He that Conquers our Averſions at the entrance of this Work, will be ſure to help our Infirmities in the Progreſs of it. Hear what <hi>David</hi> ſays, and he ſpeaks it as his own Experience; <hi>Pſalm</hi> 63.8. <hi>My Soul followeth hard after thee, thy right hand uphold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth me.</hi> Do we therefore fear, that we ſhall droop and ſink, that we ſhall flag and fail, before we have attained our End, and met with Chriſt to our Satisfaction? There is
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:51055:30"/>Cauſe enough for this fear, I confeſs, if we were to look to our ſelves only; for we are poor, feeble, ſpiritleſs Creatures, when we are left alone; but conſidering the mighty Aſſiſtance we have to depend on, this fear is cauſeleſs, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 40.31. <hi>They that wait upon the Lord, ſhall renew their Strength; they ſhall mount up with wings as Eagles,</hi> Creatures noted for ſwiftneſs in haſting to the Prey.</p>
               <p n="4">4. <hi>We are never out of our Way, while we are in the Purſuit of Chriſt.</hi> The very ſeek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of him is ſuch a ſafe and bleſſed Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment, that no Evil can befal us if we cloſely follow it. And indeed 'tis that which ought to be the continual Employment and Buſineſs of our Lives; for as long as we are Pilgrims and Sojourners, which is our State here upon Earth, we are ſtill to ſeek, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.13, 14. Chriſt may be loſt again and again in our Apprehenſion, before we leave the World; the Diſcoveries and Manifeſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions which he makes of himſelf to us now, are but Tranſient, like the ſhining of the Sun in a Cloudy Day, which often breaks out, and is as often darkned again.</p>
               <p>Chriſt draws near to the two Diſciples going to <hi>Emmaus,</hi> and walks along with them, but <hi>their Eyes were held that they could not know him,</hi> Luke 24.15, 16. Aſſoon as they knew him he vaniſhes, <hi>ver.</hi> 31. A lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle after he appears in the midſt of them, <hi>ver.</hi> 36. And then he is parted from them again, <hi>ver.</hi> 51. Therefore the ſeekers of Chriſt are in the way of Chriſt, and need not to fear.</p>
               <pb n="51" facs="tcp:51055:30"/>
               <p n="5">5. <hi>Our ſeeming Separations and Diſtances from Chriſt, ſhall Work for our Good.</hi> Gods withholding of many Things from us, which we reckon very deſirable, is as truly an Act of Mercy, as the giving of his Son to us; and his Sons withholding of himſelf as to ſenſible Fruition, may be in as much Love, as if he imparted himſelf moſt freely. Yea, why may not I ſay, that he may withhold himſelf in more Love, and make it turn more to our Advantage? Then if he imparted himſelf moſt freely. If he in all his Diſpenſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and Dealings with his own, does that which is <hi>beſt,</hi> it muſt needs be ſo. The Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men here were paſſionately concerned that <hi>their Lord was taken away;</hi> they ſaw the Place where he had lain, and they wanted to ſee him in it: But was it not much better to hear the News of his being <hi>riſen again;</hi> than to find him <hi>Dead?</hi> So poor Souls that are ſeeking of chriſt, ſhould ſuppreſs their Fears with this Conſideration, that 'tis better for them to be covered with a Cloud, than brought forth to the Light, if Chriſt think it ſo. Communion and Defertion (like <hi>Eſthers</hi> Faſt and Banquet, Sackcloath and Royal apparrel) ſhall ſerve the ſame end of their Salvation.</p>
               <p n="6">6. <hi>What we come ſhort of obtaining upon Earth, will be abundantly recompen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>'t, and made up in Heaven.</hi> Where, they that now ſeek the Lord, ſhall be <hi>ever with him,</hi> 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 4.17. If it be afar off, that we ſeek him <hi>now,</hi> 'tis our Comfort, that we ſhall have
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:51055:31"/>the neareſt views <hi>hereafter;</hi> whatever Doors, or Walls, or Latteſſes are now betwixt him and us, hereafter there ſhall be none. 'Tis uncertain, whether I may find my Beloved, ſo as I would, or ſo as perhaps I have ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times done, at this or that particular ſeaſon, in this or that particular Duty, I cannot abſolutely depend upon it; but this I may be Poſitive in, that he can withdraw him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf no longer, than while I am in this World. Nothing more certain in all the Bible, than that in Glory there will be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant ſight and full Enjoyment; and 'tis as certain that this will be may final Lot, if ſeeking with my whole Heart be my preſent Work. Every Holy Soul will drop all its fears at the Gate of Heaven, as aſhamed of them; and therefore why ſhould we indulge that fear here, that muſt be bandiſht thence?</p>
               <p n="3">III. <hi>Whence do theſe Fears ariſe,</hi> in ſuch as ſeek a Crucified Jeſus?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſwer,</hi> From four Springs.</p>
               <p n="1">. <hi>From darkneſs of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding.</hi> The Children of Light are enlightned but in part, their Knowledge is imperfect, and Miſtakes may ſometimes have as much influence upon them, as the greateſt Truths. Thus wrong Apprehenſions of Things will produce un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaſonable Fears; when a Believers way is plain and clear, he goes on Boldly and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidently; but when he is bewildred and confounded, and the Eye of his Mind over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſt,
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:51055:31"/>ſo that he cannot diſcern where he is, every Shadow will affright him. <hi>As the groſs Ignorance of Carnal Sinners is the Impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diment of their Converſion, ſo the remaining Ignorance of troubled Saints is a great hindrance of their Comfort.</hi> When the Devil Tempts or Terrifies, he does it in the Dark; he firſt caſts a Miſt before us, and then comes out like a roaring Lyon againſt us. Error in the Judgment, diſpoſes to fearfulneſs of Heart.</p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>From weakneſs of Faith.</hi> Where Fear is under the Rule and Government of Faith, 'tis never exceſſive or ſinful; but where fear gets the upper Hand of Faith, and prevailes againſt that which ought to give bounds and meaſures to it, 'tis always inordinate and ir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>regular: This was the Caſe of Chriſts Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples; <hi>Mat.</hi> 8.26. <hi>Why are ye fearful, O ye of little Faith?</hi> Our Lord does in Effect an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer his own Queſtion, for the Reaſon of their being ſo fearful, was becauſe they had ſo little Faith. Faith will hold up the Soul that's embarqued with Chriſt (as they were) in the greateſt Storms, and though the Soul may be moved with Fear, it ſhall never be ſunk. If we did but believe ſtrongly and ſtedfaſtly, we ſhould find a cure for all thoſe tremblings and toſſings which now our Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits may-be too much hurried and diſturb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with.</p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>From forgetfulneſs of the Promiſes.</hi> We have many precious Promiſes given us in the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel, which if we did receive and hold faſt they
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:51055:32"/>could not but ſilence and confute our Fears. <hi>I Remember thy Judgments</hi> (ſays <hi>David</hi>) <hi>and have Comforted my ſelf,</hi> Pſal. 119.52. When<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever we are ſinfully afraid, the Promiſes of God are out of our deliberate Thoughts; we either do not think of them at all, or think not ſo of them, as to ſix our Minds upon them. Therefore the Angel puts the Women in remembrance of what Chriſt had told them before his Death, that he would riſe again and meet them in <hi>Galilee,</hi> ver. 6. <hi>He is ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen,</hi> as <hi>he ſaid.</hi> This Promiſe of his ſeems to be forgotten and buried with him. Nay the Enemies of our Lord ſeem to take more notice of it, than the Diſciples; they thought of it ſo much, that therefore they ſecur'd his Grave that he might be hindred as they thought from riſing again.</p>
               <p n="4">4. <hi>From the Ardency of their Love.</hi> As to all the other three Springs of diſquieting fear in Believers, it may be truly ſaid, that it cometh of Evil, but it may partly pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed from this better Cauſe alſo. There is no Perſon who knows what it is <hi>to Love,</hi> but alſo knows, that the greater and more vehement our Love is to any Object, the more apt we are to be afraid of loſing it, and the more jealous and miſtruſtful upon the leaſt appearance of Alienation, or any Interruption of Converſe with it. They that Love not the Lord Jeſus, are not exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſed with any ſuch Fears concerning him; ſo that theſe fears are hopeful Evidences of a good State, though in themſelves they are not excuſable from Sin.</p>
               <pb n="55" facs="tcp:51055:32"/>
               <p n="4">IV. Uſe.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Learn, that the offence of the Croſs of Chriſt is really no Offence; and none whoſe Hearts are right and ſound can ſtum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble at it. The Women here ſought Jeſus who was Crucified, they did not ſleight him for being ſo. The Croſs of Chriſt is not a thing to be aſhamed of, but rather to be gloried in, it ſhould not prejudice us againſt Chriſt, but rather be a Motive to attract us to him.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The Memory of him that dyed for us, ought not to periſh with us. We are very prone to forget our Friends, ſoon after we have laid them in the Duſt, how amiable and ſerviceable ſoever they have been in their Lives: But Chriſt is to be everlaſting<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Remembred. The Devout Women ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſt their Reſpects to him after Death at his very Tomb.</p>
               <p n="3">3. The ſhewing forth of <hi>Chriſts Death,</hi> is as neceſſary as the belief of <hi>his Reſurrection.</hi> It is not enough for us to ſeek him as <hi>glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied,</hi> but we muſt alſo ſeek him <hi>as Crucified;</hi> ſeek him where he once was among the Dead <hi>in the Grave,</hi> as well as where he now is among the Living <hi>in Heaven.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. Let no Sinner whatſoever be afraid of ſeeking Communion with Chriſt. <hi>Mary Magdalen</hi> is particularly named here, <hi>ver.</hi> 1. See <hi>Mark</hi> 16.9. Do not ſay 'tis Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption in ſuch as you; for 'tis a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendable
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:51055:33"/>mendable Act of Faith, and wretched Inſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delity not to do it.</p>
               <p n="5">5. Let no Sinner that ſeeks, doubt of his Succeſs in ſeeking; <hi>Pſalm</hi> 69.32. <hi>The hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſhall ſee this, and be glad, and your Heart ſhall live that ſeek God.</hi> This is as true as God is true, and therefore Queſtion it at your Peril. 'Tis his faithful ſaying, and in his Name I require you to receive it, you who deſire to find out Chriſt, and be found in him, can never be loſt fro want of him.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="sermon">
               <pb n="57" facs="tcp:51055:33"/>
               <head>SERMON IV.</head>
               <head type="sub">Nov. 5. 1697.</head>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>ISA. LIV. 15.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                     <p>Behold, they ſhall ſurely gather together, but not by me: Whoſoever ſhall ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther together against thee, ſhall fall for thy ſake.</p>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>THE Great and Magnificent Promiſes which this Chapter contains, ſhew plainly enough, that they concern not ſo much the Jewiſh Church after her return out of <hi>Babylon,</hi> as the Chriſtian Church, which was to be far more glorious, in the New-Teſtament Times. The very firſt Verſe, hath a manifeſt Reference to the numerous Converſions of the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> who though formerly Barren, ſhould exceed in fruitful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs under the Goſpel; and on this Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, we read <hi>Ver.</hi> 5. <hi>That the Holy One of Iſrael,</hi> ſhould be called, <hi>the God of the whole Earth.</hi> Large Aſſurances of ſpiritual and temporal Bleſſings are given hereupon; with reſpect to the Proſperity of Souls,
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:51055:34"/>and the flouriſhing alſo of their outward State. As to this latter, we need look back no further, than <hi>ver.</hi> 14. The Words Preceding the Text; <hi>In Righteouſneſs ſhalt thou be eſtabliſhed, thou ſhalt be far from Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion, for thou ſhalt not fear, and from Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror, for it ſhall not come near thee.</hi> The Summ of which ſeems to be this; God will raiſe up ſuch righteous Magiſtrates and Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers every where in the latter Days, as that his People ſhall be deliver'd not only from Oppreſſion, but from the Fear and Terror of it too. The Church and the World have been ſeverely exercis'd with Princes, <hi>Who like Lions, have learned to catch the Prey, and devoured Men,</hi> Ezek. 19.3. Such as have removed the Bounds, <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 5.10. Tram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pled upon Laws, and invaded Properties: But there is a Time to come, when all ſuch Thrones ſhall bee caſt down, <hi>and</hi> Zion <hi>ſhall be redeem'd with Judgment, and defended with Equity.</hi> Then (may ſome ſay) ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly after this, we ſhall have no Tribulation in the World; we ſhall meet with no more Storms or Tempeſts, but enjoy Calm and ſettled Weather, without any Interrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; we ſhall have nothing to do, but to <hi>ſit under our Vines and Fig-Trees, and there will be none to Moleſt and Diſturb us</hi> from that Time forward. The Text is brought in as an Anſwer hereto; <hi>Behold, they</hi> (<hi>i. e.</hi> they that wiſh thy Hurt, that would be oppreſſing thee, as before) <hi>ſhall ſurely gather together,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>q. d.</hi> You muſt
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:51055:34"/>not think, that Sinners will be ſo entirely conſum'd out of the Earth, as that there ſhould be no Deſigns or Endeavours to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verthrow your Eſtabliſhment; As you will have the Poor always with you, to draw out your Charity, ſo you will always have ſome Enemies (though Feeble and Impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent) for the Trial of your Faith and Cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage; you'l never want ſome to unite and combine againſt you; but whoever they be, you have this for your Encouragement, I will not be on their ſide, nor take their Part, and by ſeeking your Deſtruction, they ſhall in the Iſſue, find their own.</p>
               <p>Obſ. <hi>The unwearied miſchievous Attempts of the Adverſaries of Gods People in the World, as they are made without God, ſo they ſhall end in Ruine to themſelves.</hi> Here,
<list>
                     <item>1. 1 ſhall ſhew, That the Adverſaries of God's People will be unweariedly attempt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Miſchief againſt them.</item>
                     <item>2. How thoſe Attempts are without God.</item>
                     <item>3. That they ſhall end in Ruine to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves.</item>
                     <item>4. Why they ſhall do ſo.</item>
                     <item>5. Uſe.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. To ſhew, <hi>That the Adverſaries of Gods People in the World, will be unwearied in their miſchievous Attempts againſt them.</hi> So ſays
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:51055:35"/>the Text, <hi>they ſhall gather together.</hi> This is ſure, upon various Grounds.</p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>He who foreknows all their Thoughts, Inclinations and Purpoſes from Everlaſting, hath foretold it.</hi> His is a ſure Word of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſie, and not a Tittle of it ever fail'd; and 'tis as impoſſible that finite Agents ſhould do leſs than he hath ſaid, as that they ſhould do more. He hath a full Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of all before him, and does in one undivided inſtant ſee how every Cauſe will operate, and what Effects it will produce; He can tell what he intends to ſuffer them to do, and what he intends to withhold and reſtrain them from doing: And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore if his Underſtanding cannot be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd, nor his Knowledge be miſtaken, his Predictions muſt needs be true. So when we read of <hi>Gog</hi>'s coming up, <hi>as a Cloud to cover the Land</hi> (which ſome think, is meant of a Succeſſion of the Churches E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies) and not of a ſingle Perſon; the Lord puts the Queſtion. <hi>Art thou he of whom I have ſpoken in old Time, by my Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants the Prophets of Iſrael, which Propheſied in thoſe Days, many Years, that I would bring thee againſt them?</hi> Ezek. 38.16, 17. God hath infallibly determin'd in himſelf all that ſhall be, and ſome part of thoſe Determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations are declared in his Word; and therefore nothing can fall out contrary to that Word, but every thing muſt fall out to agree with it, if it be a ſaying of God, it cannot be unfulfilled.</p>
               <pb n="61" facs="tcp:51055:35"/>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>So long as there are any of the Children of the Devil out of Hell, he will be inſpiring them with Malice againſt the Church of God on Earth.</hi> The Old Serpent will be the Old Serpent ſtill, and there is the ſame Poiſon which runs in the Veins of all his Seed. The Enmity is incurable and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortal, and not to be ſlain between the two Seeds, unleſs they were to joyn and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come one. They that Work Iniquity, and they that live Godly in Chriſt Jeſus can never amicably walk together, any more than Fire and Water can be reconciled to run quietly along in the ſame Stream. Till all Things are ſubdned to Chriſt (which will not be till the end comes, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.28.) we cannot expect that all ſhould be at perfect Peace with thoſe that are Chriſt's; for as our Lord and they that are his, are united in their Intereſts, ſo they are uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally aſſanlted with the like Opponents. The Chriſtian Society cannot look for uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal Concord and Good-will, except there were an univerſal Subjection to the Holy Founder. 'Tis no wonder, that they ſhould Act againſt Religion, who are under the full Power of natural Corruption, as many will be to the very Laſt. <hi>Wickedneſs pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedeth from the Wicked,</hi> 1 Sam. 24.13. juſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly applied by <hi>David</hi> to <hi>Sauls</hi> unreaſonable purſuit of him.</p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>The very Defeats and Diſappointments which the Enemies of the Church receive, make them to renew their attempts with greater Vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:51055:36"/>and Fury;</hi> they are not the more diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hearten'd, but the more exaſperated; not made to deſiſt, but rather provok't to go on. When God ſcatters and foils his Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſaries, they will, if poſſible, rally them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves again, and ſtrive to recover their Ground: And when their Projects are bla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted, and their Hopes periſht, they are ſo much the fuller of Rage and Revenge, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 44.25. <hi>That fruſtratcth the Tokens of the Liars, and maketh Diviners Mad.</hi> The more eminently God hath lifted up his Hand, the more inſolently have they ſtretcht out theirs; and to make amends for their being driven back, they have made the greater haſt in their next return. <hi>Pharaoh</hi> grew the harder, and more obſtinate in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſing to let <hi>Iſrael</hi> go, after God had ſent ſo many Plagues upon him; and though he did unwillingly diſmiſs them at the laſt, he would have ſatisfied his Luſt up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them, if he could have overtaken them. <hi>When Dagon was fallen upon his Face before the Ark,</hi> the ſottiſh <hi>Philiſtines</hi> took him, and ſet him in his Place again, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 5.3. Divine Appearances againſt them do not eaſily Plung them into Deſpair, but add a fierceneſs to their Spirits, and put an Edge to their Oppoſition.</p>
               <p n="4">4. <hi>The fearful Expectation of future Ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance, is a Spur to their diligent <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe of all the preſent Opportunities of ſinning.</hi> 'Tis not ſo in it ſelf, but the contrary; it ought to deter them from Sin, and excite them
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:51055:36"/>to Repentance, but through their Corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, it renders them moſt reſolvedly and deſparately Wicked. As God ſees that their Day is coming, ſo his Enemies can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but have ſome Dread and Jealouſie of it themſelves; they can hardly forbear to think (ſometimes at leaſt) that their Day of Triumph and Jollity is going over, and their Day of Reckoning and of Account is coming on; but they are the worſe by reaſon of ſuch Thoughts. As ſenſual Beaſts cry, <hi>Let us Eat and Drink, for to Morrow we Dye;</hi> 1 Cor. 15.32. So Cruel Beaſts, and inhumane Devils, quicken themſelves to acts of Barbarity, to eat the Fleſh, and drink the Blood of Saints, on the ſame Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive. Becauſe they know that Death and Judgment will ſpeedily prevent them, and they cannot do what they would, they will be eager to do what they can; if their Time be ſhort, they will hatch as much Miſchief in it, as is poſſible; as if it were their only Covetouſneſs and Ambition to ſill up the Meaſure of their Sins, before Wrath come upon them to the uttermoſt. Men of ſuch Principles and Tempers will ſurely gather together.</p>
               <p n="2">II. <hi>How are theſe unwearied Attempts a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the People of God, without God?</hi> So God himſelf ſays poſitively, here in the Text, but <hi>not by me.</hi> This may be open'd and ſtated in five Propoſitions.</p>
               <pb n="64" facs="tcp:51055:37"/>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>'Tis moſt undeniable, that the Churches Enemies can neither do, nor contrive the doing of any thing abſolutely without God.</hi> No ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Cauſe can Act but in dependance up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the firſt; no Creature can ſubſiſt, no faculty can perform any of its operations, if Providence did not concur. The worſt of Men live and move, and have their Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings in God, while they are running to do Evil; for if he ſhould ſuſpend his influence, they muſt ſtand ſtill, and ſink into no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing. The whole Power of Darkneſs would be utterly diſabled from doing any harm, as the moſt innocent Creatures are uninclin'd to it, if that Power were not upheld in its Exerciſe by a greater. All the Plots which are formed beneath, prove vain and fruitleſs, unleſs there be a Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion given from above. Proud Men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>would turn the World upſide down, but the great God carries their Counſel head<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long whenever he pleaſes, <hi>Job</hi> 5.13. If he put his Bridle in their Jaws, it will either hinder them from ſtirring, or cauſe them to err, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 30.28.</p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>It muſt be granted alſo, that the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies of the Church can do nothing effectually, but as God really employs them to be the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments of his juſt Diſpleaſure;</hi> and ſo they are frequently employ'd, being not ſit for any other Work, and on ſeveral Accounts moſt ſit for this; like the common Exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutioners in humane Courts, who are ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally the baſeſt of Men. They are ſaid
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:51055:37"/>to be ordain'd and eſtabliſh't for Correcti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, <hi>Hab.</hi> 1.12. They are called Gods Sword, and Gods Hand, <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 17.13, 14. The Rods of Gods Anger, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 10.5. The Weapons of his Indignation, <hi>Chap.</hi> 13.5. Hence it is that the King of <hi>Babylon</hi> is ſty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led God's Servant ſo often, <hi>Jer.</hi> 25.9. ch. 27.6. ch. 43.10. Becauſe God puniſht his People by his Means. When the <hi>Aſſyrian</hi> came againſt the <hi>Jews,</hi> and made ſuch ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vock and ſpoil among them, God ſent him, and gave him a Charge, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 10.7. Thus wicked Men are many Times the Meſſengers and. Commiſſioners of a Juſt and Holy God againſt his offending Children.</p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>The Attempts of Enemies againſt Gods People are notwithſtanding, without God's Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probation.</hi> God permits many Things to be done which he approves not the doing of; and therefore we are not to fetch our warrant from Providence, but from the Word. Whatſoever is againſt the Rule of Gods revealed Will, is not by him; for we muſt go according to that, or elſe we walk contrary to him, and Sin in what we do. On this Account God entred that complaint againſt his People, <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 8.4. <hi>The have ſet up Kings, but not by me; they have made Princes, and I knew it not</hi> (which muſt be underſtood of his approving Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge; as Chriſt is ſaid not to know <hi>the Workers of Iniquity,</hi> Luke 13.27.) That which the Prophet refers to, is the falling off of the Ten Tribes of <hi>Iſrael</hi> from the
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:51055:38"/>Houſe of <hi>David</hi> to <hi>Jeroboam;</hi> God ſays expreſly, that this Thing was from him, 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 12.23. Providentially order'd and diſpos'd by him, as well as foretold, <hi>Chap.</hi> 11.31. Yet they ſiun'd, becauſe God had given the Kingdom to <hi>David</hi> and his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily for ever, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 13.5. And to that Family they owed Subjection.</p>
               <p n="4">4. <hi>The Attempts of Enemies, when they have moſt Succeſs, are without God's truly fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour able Preſence.</hi> None of the Adverſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of the Church can ever lay any Claim to that gracious Promiſe, which belongs pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cullarly to the Church her ſelf, <hi>I am with thee.</hi> God hath no reſpect to their Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fons, even when he ſhines upon their Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels; nor is it out of Kindneſs to them, but to ſignifie how he is diſpleaſed with his Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple. Treacherous Dealers are counted hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py oftentimes, and appear to be ſo; for God Plants them, yea they take Root, they Grow, yea they bring forth Fruit, as the Prophet ſpeaks with a remarkable Grada<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, <hi>Jer.</hi> 12.1, 2. But there is nothing of the real Love and Good-will of God in all this; they are the Objects of his hatred and loathing at the ſame time; he abhorrs them, and beholds them afar off. Theſe Diſpenſations, though ſuch as they deſire, and are pleaſed with, are no Tokens of Mercy; Their Proſperity is a Curſe and a Plague, but not a Bleſſing.</p>
               <p n="5">5. <hi>The Attempts of Enemies at that Time, which the Prophet here hath a Relation to, will
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:51055:38"/>be without Gods Aſſiſtanee, and conſequently without Succeſs.</hi> God will not ſo much as ſeemingly favour them alays; but when he hath perform'd his whole Work by them, he'll make them know that they are but Men, <hi>Pſalm</hi> 9.20. Poor weak Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, when his Power is withdrawn from them. <hi>I have Created the Waſter to deſtroy,</hi> ſays God, <hi>ver.</hi> 16. of this Chapter, the Words following the Text; but what can the Waſter do alone, more than any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Creature of God? What can he do when God hath no further uſe to make of him, when Deſtructions are come to a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petual End? This Text gives ground for the Expectation of ſuch a Time; wherein all the Commiſſions of evil Men from God againſt his People ſhall finally expire. Though they may falfly pretend and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume otherwiſe, as in the Caſe of <hi>Senna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cherib,</hi> which the Event confuted, 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 18.35. <hi>Am I now come up without the Lord againſt this Place to deſtroy it?</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p n="3">III. <hi>That all theſe Attempts of the Adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries of God's People will iſſue in Ruine to themſelves.</hi> So we read here; <hi>Whoſoever ſhall gather together ſhall fall,</hi> &amp;c. Their fall is as certain as their gathering together, and ſo muſt neceſſarity be, if we conſider theſe ſix Things.</p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>The greateſt Attempt which was ever made by the Devil againſt the Church, in the
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:51055:39"/>Perſon of Chriſt himſelf, became the Means of ſubverting his own Kingdom. Herod, and Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late, with the Gentiles, and the Children of Iſrael were all gathered together</hi> by the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtigation of Satan againſt our Lord Jeſus, <hi>Acts</hi> 4.27. But what was the Iſſue? <hi>He was ſet as King upon his Holy Hill of Zion,</hi> Pſalm 2.6. And they were broken and daſht in Pieces, <hi>like a Potters Veſſel,</hi> ver. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. The Devil thought he had laid the Ax to the Root then, and ſhould have cut down all the Hopes of God's People at once; but he then receiv'd the greateſt and moſt fatal blow. Our dying Redeemer by Death deſtroyed the Deſtroyer, triumpht over Principalities and Powers; and he hath the Promiſe of the Father, that all Enemies ſhall be put under his Feet. The Head of the Serpent is irrecoverably bruis'd, and ſo ſhall thoſe other Dragons be, which are no better than his Seed and Spawn, <hi>Pſaim</hi> 110.6. <hi>He ſhall wound the Heads over many Countreys.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>The ſtanding of the Churches Enemies, is the most precarious and uncertain Thing; not like that of the Church upon a Rock, an Everlaſting Foundation, but a ſandy, deceitful Bottom.</hi> Pſalm 73.18. <hi>Surely thou didſt ſet them in ſlippery Places:</hi> Places which they hold and poſſeſs, meerly at the Pleaſure of God, which they cannot ſettle or faſten themſelves in, at their own Will; Places, ſometimes of the greateſt heighth, but pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portionably of the greateſt Danger, from
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:51055:39"/>whence, while they are dazled with the Light ſhining on their Ways, they com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly tumble on a ſudden. They ſtand the longer, that they may the leſs ſuſpect their fall; and God does conceal the exact Period of teir ſtanding, with this Deſign, that their fall may be the more ſurprizing. They ſtand only till their Iniquities are compleated, till the Judgments of God are Ripe to be inflicted, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> till they have worn out the Leaſe of limited Time, and Wrath is ready to break forth; and how ſoon this may be, they can never tell.</p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>All that they have or can have to Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port and Deſend them, will not be ſufficient, when their appointed Deſtruction comes.</hi> What can be the Strength or Stability of the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies of God in his Day of Viſitation, who ſhakes the very Earth out of her Place, ſo that the Pillars thereof cremble? What can bear up thoſe, whom her hath purpoſed to throw down? <hi>If he will not withdraw his Anger, the Proud helpers do ſtoop under him,</hi> Job 9.13. They that think to Protect their Confederates from the ſtroke of God, may feel it and ſhare in it themelves, but can never Guard another Perſon againſt it, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 31.3. <hi>When the Lord ſhall ſtretch out his Hand, both he that helpeth, ſhall fall, and he that is holpen, ſhall fall down, and they all ſhall fall together.</hi> Every Creature that of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers to do ſervice, will he a Part of the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice, when God comes in his Garments of Vengeance. Even Beaſts are threaten'd
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:51055:40"/>with Men, <hi>Zech.</hi> 12.4. Chap. 14.12, with 15. compared, And God's rebuke on ſuch is Recorded, <hi>Pſalm</hi> 76.6.</p>
               <p n="4">4. <hi>The Enemies of the Church are rais'd up for this Purpoſe, that God may Honour himſelf upon them. Pharaob</hi> is an inſtance of it; <hi>exod.</hi> 9.16. <hi>In very Deed, for this cauſe have I raiſed thee up, to ſhew in thee my Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er and that my Name may be declared through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out all the Earth.</hi> God would never ſuffer ſuch Monſters to Tyrannize over the beſt of Mankind, and to Reproach and Blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheme him, as they ordinarily do, if he had not ſome Ends to bring about, that would be honourable to himſelf, and degra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to them at laſt. As long as they ſill their Thrones of Iniquity, and keep their seats of Violence, the Majeſty of Heaven is contemn'd and vilified: And if they ſhould go off with Impunity, his Glory would be loſt. And therefore we may be ſure, this ſhall not be; if God be ſo Jealous for his own Name, that he will be ſanctified in the needful Correction of his own People, we cannot imagine, that he will fail to vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicate himſelf by the juſt revenging of his Adverſaries.</p>
               <p n="5">5. <hi>The greateſt Enemies that the Church of God ever yet had, have fallen; though as like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to ſland once, as any now or hereafter can be.</hi> How have all the Parts of the Image in <hi>Nebuchadnezzar</hi>'s Prophetical Dream been ſmitten one after another? Who does not know, that there hath been a ſucceſſive Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:51055:40"/>of all the Four Grand Monarchies and Empires of the World? Was not the <hi>Babylonian</hi> pull'd down by the <hi>Perſian,</hi> the <hi>Perſian</hi> tript up by the <hi>Graecian,</hi> the <hi>Grae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cian</hi> ſunk by the <hi>Roman,</hi> and the <hi>Roman</hi> at length loſt and ſwallowed by the <hi>Papal</hi> Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er? What's become of all the formidable Men of Blood, that have ſlain their Thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands, and ten Thouſands, and not been ſatisfied? <hi>Have they not born their ſhame with them that go down to the Pit, though they cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Terrour in the Land of the Living?</hi> Ezek. 32.24. What are they that breath out Threatnings now, better or mightier than they that have periſht in all Ages before them?</p>
               <p n="6">6. <hi>The preſent Enemies of the Church have indeed begun to fall; which is au hopeful To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken that they ſhall ſurely fall.</hi> And whether the preſent Enemies may be the laſt or not, I think, 'tis beyond all Controverſie, that they are the worſt which can be. Now that there are certain beginnings of their Ruine is hardly to be doubted alſo. It was ſounded long ſince in Propheſie, <hi>Babylon is fallen, is fallen,</hi> Rev. 14.8. And without any nice and curious Obſervation, we may diſcern that the Building cracks. Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt hath been conſuming eminently ever ſince the Reformation one hundred and eighty Years, by the Spirit of Chriſts Mouth in the Preaching of the Goſpel, according to 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.8. He hath been driven out of theſe Nations, and ſeveral other Countrys,
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:51055:41"/>into which we hope, he ſhall never re-enter. Many Learned and Holy Men have batter'd the <hi>Roman Jericho</hi> a great while with invin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible Arguments; and Miniſters, like the Prieſts of Old, continue Blowing with their Trumpets; we only wait for ſuch a Breath of God, and Shout of the People, that the Walls may fall down flat and the City be taken.</p>
               <p n="4">IV. <hi>Why ſhall the Attempts of the Enemies of God's People end thus in their own Ruine?</hi> The Text acquaints us with this likewiſe; they ſhall fall <hi>for thy ſalke. Quest.</hi> How is this to be underſtood?</p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>Some read the Words, they ſhall fall</hi> before thee, <hi>that thou mayst ſee it.</hi> The God who is now ſecretly carrying on their intended Ruine, which is the matter of thy Faith, ſhall at length viſibly accompliſh it in thy open view, to thy Comfort and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joycing. So <hi>Prov.</hi> 29.16. <hi>the Righteous ſhall ſee their fall.</hi> Pſalm 52.5, 6. <hi>God ſhall deſtroy thee for ever, he ſhall take thee away,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>The Righteous alſo ſhall ſee,</hi> &amp;c. So <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael ſaw that great Work which the Lord did upon the Egyptians,</hi> Exod. 14.31. The Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions which ſuch ſights make upon ſuch witneſſes, render them deſirable, though awful, <hi>Jer.</hi> 20.12. <hi>Let me ſee thy Vengeance on them.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>For thy ſake, cannot be meant, for thy Merit, but for thy Good and Benefit.</hi> So
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:51055:41"/>
                  <hi>Mal.</hi> 3.11. <hi>I will rebuke the Devourer for your ſakes;</hi> not becauſe you deſerve it (the People of God never did that) but that you may have the Advantage of it. Their Deſtruction is to make way for your Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, <hi>Prov.</hi> 11.8. <hi>The Righteous is deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver'd out of trouble, and the Wicked cometh in his ſtead.</hi> Pſalm 141.10. <hi>Let the Wicked fall into their own Net, while that I withal eſcape.</hi> They muſt fall, that the Church of God may riſe; for while they ſtand, the Church is kept under. <hi>Babylon</hi> muſt come down into the Duſt, that <hi>Zion</hi> may be lift<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed up out of it.</p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>For thy ſake, may be meant, for the Kindneſs and Care which I bear to thee,</hi> q. d. For thy ſake, whom I am ſo mindful of, ſo watchful over, and ſo delighted in, and have ſuch an affectionate Regard to; thou art the Object which I have in my Eye, anhd my Compaſſion and Good-will are the Springs and Reaſons of my pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed actings and appearances on thy be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>half. God Loves his own ſo well, that as he upholds the World on their Account, ſo on their Account he will deſtroy any Part of it, which is injurious to them. Therefore they are much miſtaken, who level them with other People; as <hi>Ezek.</hi> 25.8. <hi>Behold, the Houſe of Judah is like un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to all the Heathen.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="74" facs="tcp:51055:42"/>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>Security and diſtruſt are ſinful Extreams, and both of them equally to be avoided.</hi> To preſume that Enemies will not g ather to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, and to deſpair of their fall, are flat Contradictions to the Text. To ſay that the Church of God ſhall not be aſſaulted, is againſt Scripture. To ſay, <hi>That ſhe ſhall not be moved,</hi> is what the Holy Ghoſt ſays, <hi>Pſalm</hi> 46.5. We ought not to fall aſleep, or to dwell careleſsly; nor yet ſhould fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs ſurprize us, or horror overwhelm us. We have a mixture of Good and of Evil Tidings; like Milk and Honey, to temper the Wormwood and the Gall, there is enough on one Hand to awaken us, and on the other to encourage us. <hi>Aſſociate your ſelves, O ye People</hi> (there's Matter of prudent Fear) <hi>and ye ſhall be broken in Pieces;</hi> (there's Matter of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable Hope) <hi>Iſa.</hi> 8.9.</p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>A People dear to God, and peculiarly intereſted in him, are in a far more bleſſed Condition, than all the Earth beſides.</hi> God will do any Thing, or undo any thing for their ſake, he will Cut off Nations, tread upon Princes, remove Crowns and Scepters out of the way, for their ſake, Enemies cannot do ſo great Things againſt them, but that God will do as great for them, and much greater, <hi>Joel</hi> 2.20, 21. All the ſpecialities of Providence are upon their Account, and if any thing extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary happen at any Time in the World, we may be Conſident, it is for their Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice.
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:51055:42"/>As God is their God, ſo he is their pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiar Saviour, and therein they have the preheminence to all other People whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, <hi>Deut.</hi> 33.29. <hi>Happy art thou, oh Iſrael, who is like unto thee, oh People ſaved by the Lord?</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>The greateſt Danger which God's People are or can be in, is when they engage God a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them by Sin, and provoke him to fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour their Adverſaries.</hi> 'Tis poſſible that God may for the Chaſtiſement of his Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, turn away his Wrath from their fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling Enemies, <hi>Prov.</hi> 24.18. i. e. To puniſh us, they may for a while eſcape unpuniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; and during that Time they may ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, in ſome Senſe by God; and then one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly are they terrible and dreadful. When God lengthens out their Chain, and lets them looſe upon his People, none can fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſee the Spoil and Deſolation which they may be empowered to make; otherwiſe we might boldly and ſtoutly bid defiance to them.</p>
               <p n="4">4. <hi>The Obſtructions of Mercy are on our Part, and not on god's.</hi> If any ask, why this Word is not fulfilled, and all our Enemies thrown down, the Anſwer is eaſie, becauſe we our ſelves do help to hold them up. They would fall for our ſake, if they did not ſtand by our Means. Two Things eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially prolong <hi>Babylons</hi> Reprieve; the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reformed, and the divided State of the <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Churches.</p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>The unreformed State.</hi> Our Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:51055:43"/>is yet too imperfect; and many inſtead of advancing it, are apt to put it back; being fond of retaining <hi>Egyptian</hi> Fleſh-pots as a part of their Diet ſtill. Many that profeſs to come out from among them, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach too near to them. And even where the Purity of Religious Worſhip is moſt ſtrictly maintain'd, the Power of Practical Godlineſs is too much wanting. There is a lamentable degeneracy among the beſt; that we may ſay, as <hi>Lam.</hi> 4.1. <hi>How is the Gold become dim! thr most fine Gold changed.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>Their divided State.</hi> Enemies joyn Hand in Hand, and their Arms are made ſtrong, by the Differences and Quarrels of our Friends. Our ſworn Murderers that thirſt for our Blood have the fairer Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunities to purſue their Deſigns, when upon every Difference we are ready to take one another by the Throat. The diſtur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bance of <hi>Jeruſalems</hi> Peace by her own Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, is really a ſeeking of <hi>Rome</hi>'s Proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity; but a firm and hearty and (as much as may be) extenſive Union among our ſelves, would haſten the diſſolving of the Antichriſtian Conſtitution.</p>
               <p n="5">5. <hi>The Memorials of paſt Mercies are to be proſerv'd for our Support in future Difficulties. Moſes</hi>'s Rod was laid up, wherewith won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders had been wrought; and ſo was <hi>Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liah</hi>'s Sword, wherewith his own Head had been Cut off, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 21.9. Former Experien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces are often improv'd in Scripture as Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments with God, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 20.7. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 51.9,
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:51055:43"/>10. No wonder that Faith dies, upon any emergent Hazard, when ſuch gracious Acts of God are buried in forgetfulneſs, and not ſo much as a Monumental Stone erected o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver their Graves. Therefore,</p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>Let us keep alive the remembrance of this Days Deliverances.</hi> For God hath up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on this Day twice given convincing An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwers to that tempting Queſtion. <hi>Is the Lord among us?</hi> Exod. 17.7. The ſame God who blew up the Powder-Traitors, ſet his Hand again a ſecond Time, to reſcue us from their fiery Succeſſors. And this lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Work of God ſeems to have been the greateſt; for the ſhifting and altering of Governments, is one of the moſt illuſtrious Proofs of God's Soveraign Dominion; <hi>Jer.</hi> 49.38. <hi>I will ſet my Throne in Elam, and will deſtroy from thence the King, and the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, ſaith the Lord.</hi> God hath ſnatcht us from between their Teeth, who, if they could once have ſwallow'd us up, would ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver have vomited us out alive; theſe Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons have not only heard, but felt how cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el their tenderneſs is; and therefore we may juſtly reckon our ſelves deliver'd from the worſt of Deaths. And even our Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies themſelves are happily deliver'd from the occaſions of ſuch Sin; for where Men's Hearts are full of miſchievous Devices, 'tis a Mercy (if they would value and improve it as ſuch) to be depriv'd of Power to exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute and accompliſh them.</p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>Let us live as a People deliver'd from
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:51055:44"/>our ſpiritual Enemies, who would be far more hurtful to us, and ought to be much more hate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful.</hi> A Deliverance from Sin and Satan is the moſt glorious of all, and indeed without this, all our temporal Deliverances will but aggravate our Everlaſting Deſtruction. Let Sinners go to Chriſt, and let Believers Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umph in Chriſt, as ſuch a Deliverer, and ſeeing there is a ſacred Feaſt appointed to Commemorate this Deliverance, let us keep it with all thankfulneſs, and take care to Live up to the ſolemn Obligations of it.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:51055:44"/>
            <head>Books Printed for <hi>Tho Parkhurſt</hi> at the <hi>Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble</hi> and <hi>Three Crowns</hi> at the Lower End of <hi>Cheapſide.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>A Body of Practical Divinity, conſiſting of above 176 Sermons, on the Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblies Shorter Catechiſm, by <hi>Tho. Watſon</hi> formerly Miniſter of St. <hi>Stephens Walbrook, London.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Sermons and Diſcourſes on ſeveral Divine Subjects, by the late Reverend and Learned Divine, Mr. <hi>David Clarkſon,</hi> ſometime Fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low of <hi>Clare-Hall, Cambridge.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Acts, Deciſions, Decrees and Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nons of the Reformed Churches in <hi>France;</hi> being a moſt faithful Hiſtory of the riſe, growth and decay of the Reformed Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in that Kingdom. By <hi>John Quick</hi> Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter in <hi>London.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Dr. <hi>Wallis</hi>'s Theological Diſcourſes on ſeveral Occaſions, with his Letters in Vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dication of the Holy Trinity.</p>
            <p>Pacification touching the Doctrinal Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent among our United Brethren in <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don;</hi> being an Anſwer to Mr. <hi>Williams</hi> and Mr. <hi>Lobb</hi> both, who have appealed in one Point (collected for an Error) to this Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor, for his Determination about it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Mediocria:</hi> Or the middle way between Proteſtant and Papiſt; in a Paper of Juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication. The ſecond Edition with Adniti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and a Letter to Mr. <hi>Williams.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Righteouſneſs of God revealed in the Goſpel; or an impartial Enquiry into the genuine Doctrine of St. <hi>Paul,</hi> in the great but much controverted Article of Juſtificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.
<pb facs="tcp:51055:45"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> are prefixed the Epiſtles of the Right Reverend the Biſhops of <hi>Worceſter <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> and <hi>Cheſter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Friendly Interpoſer between the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors of thoſe Papers; the one called, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Report;</hi> the other, <hi>AS rebuke of that Report</hi> In order to Reconciliation, between th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Presbyterians and Independants. All fou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> by Mr. <hi>John Humfrey.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>An Account of the Bleſſed. Trinity, ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gued from the Nature and Perfection of the Supream Spirit, coincident with the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture-Doctrine, in all the Articles of the Catholick Creed: By <hi>Will, Burrough,</hi> Rector of <hi>Chenis</hi> in <hi>Bucks.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>scripture Juſtification: Or, a Diſcourſe of Juſtification, according to Scripture-Light By <hi>Samuel Clark,</hi> M. A.</p>
            <p>A Sermon Preached on the Late Day o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Thankſgiving, <hi>Decemb.</hi> 2. 1697. By <hi>Joh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Howe,</hi> Miniſter of the Goſpel; to which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> prefixt Dr. <hi>Bates</hi>'s Congratulatory Speech <hi>Nov.</hi> 22. 1697. To the King, in the Name of the Diſſenting Miniſters in and abo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>London.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Comfort in Death: A Funeral Sermon Preached upon the Death of Mr. <hi>Tim. Cruſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> Late Paſtor of a Church in <hi>London;</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Mat. Mead.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Diſcourſes upon the Rich Man and <hi>Laza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus,</hi> by <hi>Tim. Cruſo.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:51055:45"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
